<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fragmenta aulica. Or, Court and state jests in noble drollery True and reall. Ascertained to their times, places and persons. By T. S. Gent.</title>
            <author>T. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200892</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2041:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fragmenta aulica. Or, Court and state jests in noble drollery True and reall. Ascertained to their times, places and persons. By T. S. Gent.</title>
                  <author>T. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 144, [12] p., [1] leaf of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Marsh at the Princes Armes in Chancery-lane near Fleetstreet; and Jos. Coniers at the Black-Raven in the long walk near ChristChurch,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes engraved frontispiece with title: Curia and incuria.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 10 reads: Court and state jests. Or, Noble drollery.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Court and state drollery.</note>
                  <note>Includes index and three final pages of advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English wit and humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Curia quasi Incuria</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ld by Hen: Marſh. and Ios: Coniers. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>frontispiece</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fragmenta Aulica.</hi> OR, COURT AND State Jeſts IN Noble Drollery.</p>
            <p>TRUE and REALL. Aſcertained to their <hi>Times, Places</hi> and <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By T. S. Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Marſh</hi> at the <hi>Princes Armes</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> near <hi>Fleetſtreet;</hi> and <hi>Joſ. Coniers</hi> at the <hi>Black-Raven</hi> in the long Walk near Chriſt Church, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:4"/>
            <head>TO THE COURT.</head>
            <p>WE invite you here to theſe <hi>Fragmenta Aulica</hi> peices of wit and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivity, which make up the whole entertainment of the laſt ſeven Reignes of our (and their cotemporary) Princes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:5"/>
            <p>Some few ſcraps of theſe have been publiſhed in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellanies and common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of vulgar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and like ſuch iſſues have wanted both name and place, being meerly fathered on the credulous <hi>Reader;</hi> Such princely <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito</hi> ſtories proving meer <hi>popular cheats</hi> and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures.</p>
            <p>Theſe falſe citations are here rectifyed, the antique Authority of them cleared, being (as by their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous circumſtances will appear) truly reduced to
<pb facs="tcp:29474:5"/>their undoubted originals; both Hiſtory and other tracts of the times having been carefully and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately conſidered.</p>
            <p>Being thus aſſembled &amp; in this train and Equipage, they returne to the place from whence they came as the ſuitableſt and fitteſt for their reception.</p>
            <p>There will be room e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough amidſt the throng of your buſineſſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, for their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and if the Genius of the place be not different from what it was, as <hi>Paſquil</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:29474:6"/>thinks not, they may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps juſtle out more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous difficulties, and finde ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier acceſſe and attainment: as the aire inſinuates it ſelf where the other heavier and dull Elements cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed or move of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Some have wondred that among all the offices at Court whoſe vacancies have been ſupplyed, none have taken the reverſion of <hi>Archee;</hi> The publiſher therefore of theſe Joco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeria officiouſly ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes himſelf as to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.
<pb facs="tcp:29474:6"/>Others offended with the times, and the nature, name, and quality of the place, think the whole collective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken to be a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative body, of that venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble function, and that there is no want or need of him; theſe are mad-men becauſe they are not as fine fools as formerly.</p>
            <p>But the reaſon is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the conſtant ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which intermits not nor can be interrupted; ſo that it ſhould need to be peiced by borrowed mirth, the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parties</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:29474:7"/>of his own <hi>ſerene</hi> thoughts naturally indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his leyſure ſuch ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, beyond the ſtrains of the quickeſt and faceteſt invention.</p>
            <p>There are beſides many very excellent in this way of <hi>Droll</hi> who are perſons of the higheſt Honour, that contribute much to this kinde of recreation, and 'tis all the unhappineſs of theſe Collections, that they cannot trace nor recover the quickneſſe of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes: ſo that very few modern <hi>Joco's</hi> are here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted:
<pb facs="tcp:29474:7"/>but there is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon to be given of it, becauſe the preſentneſſe of the time will not ſuffer them.</p>
            <p>Theſe your diſports and trifles we poor mortals ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire as Oracles, and conceit our diſcourſe highly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, if we can draw in one of theſe ſtories by the head and eares to embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and ſet it off: in earneſt they are of as much profit as delight, having a ſmatch or <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the Humor of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>etent
<pb facs="tcp:29474:8"/>view they are ſubmitted, with a preſumption they will not be, even to you, uſeleſſe and unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours T. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29474:8"/>
            <head>COURT AND STATE <hi>JESTS.</hi> OR, Noble Drollery.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Company of little Boyes were by their Schoolmaſter not many yeares ſince appointed to Act the play of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and one who had the preſence (or the abſence rather) as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29474:9"/>being of a whining voice, puling ſpirit, conſumptive body, was appointed to perſonate King <hi>Henry</hi> himſelfe, only becauſe he had the richeſt cloaths, and his Parents the beſt people of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but when he had ſpoke his ſpeech rather like a Mouſe then a Man, one of his fellow Actors told him; If you ſpeak not <hi>HOH</hi> with a better ſpirit and voyce, your Parliament will not grant you a Farthing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queen Elizabeth.</head>
               <p>QUeen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a great lover of her Clergy eſpecially of the perſons and acquaintance of thoſe of the Prelacy or the next dignities to it, took much delight in, and highly valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the company of one Doctor <hi>David Whithead</hi> an accurate diſputant and a very facetious perſon of a conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bluntneſs, wherein one handſome claſh or reported hapned. The Queen one day, who had not the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29474:9"/>for married Clergy men ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him <hi>Whithead, I love thee the better becauſe thou art unmarried.</hi> In truth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſaid he I like you the worſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are unmarried.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Henry Cary.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry Cary</hi> Lord Hunſdon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a Kin to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Anceſtor to the Honourable Houſes of <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Monmouth,</hi> was a ſtout and great ſpirited Gentleman very cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick but not malicious and a lover of men of their Hands. Once one Mr. <hi>Colt</hi> to whom he owed a grudge, met him coming from his Houſe at <hi>Hunſdon</hi> to <hi>London</hi> with a Lordly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, my Lord gave <hi>Colt</hi> a box of the eare, <hi>Colt</hi> preſently returned it with intereſt, therupon my Lord ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants drawing their ſwords ſwarmed about him: you Rogues (ſaid the L<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.) may not I and my Neighbour change a blow but you muſt interpoſe? ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29474:10"/>the quarrel began and ended in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Treaſurer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LYonel</hi> Lord <hi>Cranfeild</hi> bred a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>London,</hi> who was ſaid to be his Tutor and own univerſity, was eſpecially converſant about the Cuſtome-houſe which was the ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of his Fortune, He being made Lord Treaſurer by King <hi>James,</hi> 1612. having married a Kinſwoman of the D. of <hi>Buckingham</hi> thought himſelfe able not only to ſtand with out, but in ſome caſes againſt him, which the Duke not enduring, he was outed of his <hi>Treaſurersſhip</hi> after he had held it four years, and fined to the King in a very great ſumme.</p>
               <p>How ever loſing his Office he ſaved himſelfe departing from that Office in an Age when it was hard to keep it. Inſomuch <hi>that one asking what was good to preſerve life</hi> was anſwered <hi>get to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29474:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord Treaſurer, for they ſeldome dye in their Places,</hi> proved to be true for four ſucceſſions.</p>
               <p>The Office of Lord Treaſurer was alwayes beheld as a place of great truſt and profit. One well skilled in the perquifit ther of being demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what he conceived the yearly value of the place might be worth made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That it might be <hi>worth ſome thouſands of pounds</hi> to him who after his death would <hi>goe inſtantly to heaven, twice as much to him</hi> who <hi>would goe to Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>No body knowes</hi> what to him who would adventure to go to Hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cheife Juſtice.</head>
               <p>THe Cheife Juſtice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas is in place beneath in profit above the Lord cheife Juſtice, for this reaſon Sir <hi>Edward Montague</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights being demanded the reaſon of degrading himſelfe from the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29474:11"/>Kings bench to the other cheife juſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip anſwered, <hi>I am now an old man and love the Kitchin better then the Hall, the warmeſt place beſt ſuiting with my Age.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kings Wardrope.</head>
               <p>IN the Kings Wardrope is a rich peice of <hi>Arras</hi> preſenting the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in 88. which at ſeverall audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ambaſſadors hath been uſed for magnificence in the banqueting Houſe (as in Cromwels uſurpation) and wherein were wrought the living portractures of the cheifeſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in that ſervice: on a time a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain who highly prized himſelfe and his valour in that naval fight, coming to Court and miſſing his picture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, complained of the injury to his friend profeſſing of himſelfe that he merited a place there as well as ſome therein remembred for that he was engaged in the middle of the fight. Be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29474:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>content ſaid his friend, thou haſt been an old Pyrate and art reſerved for another hanging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Shoomaker no Gentleman.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Philip Calthrop</hi> a very merry Gentleman of the County of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> being newly come from Court where he had obſerved the faſhion to be upon great dayes in thoſe times of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh to wear gownes of light coloured cloath, ſent to his Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in <hi>Norwich</hi> as much cloth of fine <hi>French</hi> Tawney as would make him ſuch a veſture. It happened one <hi>John Drakes</hi> a Shoomaker of ſome wealth coming into the ſhop liked it ſo well that he went &amp; bought of the ſame as much for himſelf, enjoyning the Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor to make it exactly after the faſhion he made the Knights, who ſending for his Gowne by his ſervant, he eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another of the ſame in the ſhop and enquiring whoſe it was, the Maſter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29474:12"/>told him, and the order he had for the making it up. This being told ſir <hi>Philip</hi> he ſent a new command that the Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor ſhould cut in his as many holes and ſlaſhes as his knife and ſheares could find place for and ſo ſend it him: which he did and accordingly cut the Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers in the very ſame manner and carried it home, where Prince <hi>Criſpin</hi> began to be wroth but underſtanding it was the mode that the Knights was made his combe fell ſaying he would be a <hi>Gentleman</hi> no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> William Clark.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>William Clark</hi> a Gentleman much converſant in Court, a great Maſquer and acceptable to the Ladies being a man of excellent ſhape and goodly feature and proportion, was one night at a Maſque in <hi>Whitball</hi> where were preſent King <hi>JAMES</hi> and Queen <hi>Anne;</hi> after a ſcene or two he having ſome Office or charge for that night while the ſtage was free paſſed over to the other ſide about ſome buſineſſe and with ſuch a ſtately
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29474:12"/>and ſtrutting pace befitting his preſent employment, that a Lady knowne unto him thinking to put a jeere upon him ſaid Sir—pray have a care you hurt not your ſelfe by ſtradling ſo wide I wonder what ayles you; to whom he he preſently and openly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, In troth Madam if you had that betwixt your legs which I have it would make you ſtraddle a great deal wider.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Spencer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RObert</hi> Lord <hi>Spencer</hi> Baron of <hi>Wormleighton</hi> being a Man of a quick and clear ſpirit, ſpeaking one day in <hi>Parliament</hi> of the valour of their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anceſtors in defending the Liberties of the Nation, the Earle of <hi>Arundel</hi> ſtood up and replyed, your Anceſtors were keeping of ſheep (that Lord and his Predeceſſors being known for the greateſt Sheep-maſters in <hi>England</hi>) when thoſe Liberties were defended. If they were a keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſheep returned the other, yours
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29474:13"/>were then in plotting of Treaſon. This animoſity for the preſent coſt both of them a confinement, yet ſo that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the upper Houſe ordered repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to this Lord <hi>Spencer</hi> as firſt and cauſeleſſely provoked.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Doctor Preſton.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Preſton</hi> was the greateſt Pupil-monger in <hi>England</hi> in Mans memory, having ſixteen fellow Commoners moſt Heires to faire eſtates admitted in one year in <hi>Queens Colledge,</hi> and provided convenient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodations for them. As <hi>William</hi> the popular Earle of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> was ſaid to have won a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject from the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to his own party every time he put off his Hat, ſo it was commonly ſaid in the Colledge that every time Mr. <hi>Preſton</hi> plucked off his Hat to Dr. <hi>Davenant</hi> the Maſter, he gained a Chamber or Study for one of his Pupils, among
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29474:13"/>whom one <hi>Chambers</hi> a <hi>Londoner</hi> was eminent for his learning. Being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards choſen himſelfe Maſter of <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Colledge,</hi> he removed thither with moſt of his Pupils, and when it was much admired where all theſe ſhould find lodging in that Colledge which was ſo full already, one replyed, Mr. <hi>Preſton will carry</hi> Chambers <hi>along with him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas More.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Thomas More</hi> being committed to the <hi>Tower</hi> for refuſing the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> being, as in his time it was, the cuſtome, and alſo to our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory obſerved, that the Priſoners there were not dieted at their own but the <hi>Kings</hi> charges, the Lieutenant of the <hi>Tower</hi> providing their food for them: when the ſaid Lieutenant one day ſaid unto him by way of comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he was ſorry his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were no better, <hi>I like ſaid Sir
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29474:14"/>Thomas the dyet very well, and if I diſlike it, turn me out of Doores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Courtier coming to him, while in reſtraint, with proffer of mercy from the King if he would comply with his <hi>Majeſties</hi> will, and take the ſaid Oath, he replyed that <hi>His minde was now changed,</hi> whereupon the Courtier departed, and told the King that Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> would ſubmit himſelf to his grace in that matter, which the King willing to accept, gave him order to repaire to the <hi>Tower</hi> again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in a forme under his hand. At his return challening Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> with his promiſe, he wondring told him that he meant only by changing his minde, that whereas he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſhave himſelfe before his Execution, he would now let his beard ſuffer with his head: to the abaſhment of the man, who ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently had informed the King of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his converſion.</p>
               <p>The ſame Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> during his Chancellorſhip, had his Lady well at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by a handſome retinue, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29474:14"/>at going to Church, living then in <hi>Chelſey,</hi> where her Gentleman-uſher alwayes after my Lord was out of his ſeat after Sermon, uſed to wait upon his Lady, telling her Madam my Lord is gone. It hapned that upon this ſcore of the ſupremacy ſir <hi>Thomas</hi> was put from that dignity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the next Sunday after as ſoon as Church was done, (having the week before diſmiſt moſt of his ſervants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to live privately,) he came to his Ladies Pew himſelfe, and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her alone in paſſing, <hi>Madam my Lord is gone,</hi> (meaning the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,) and ſo walkt home before her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Pallavicin Horatio.</head>
               <p>ONe <hi>Seignior Pallavicin</hi> a <hi>Genoeſe</hi> who lived in <hi>England</hi> a kin to Sir <hi>Horatio,</hi> boaſting of his Nobility and high extraction, as deſcended from an illuſtrious Houſe, was thus anſwered by a blunt Citizen (who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29474:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>from mean Parentage had riſen to great wealth, reputation and honor, <hi>and ſo I (ſaith he) alſo am come of an illuſtrious Houſe, where the Sun con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſhone through the rotten walls and roofes thereof.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>My Lord Bacon.</head>
               <p>IT is ſtoried of my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> (to his advantage) that when he was Lord Chancellor he had two ſervants one in all cauſes Patron to the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe (whom charity preſumed always injured the other to the Defendant (pittying him as compelled to Law) but taking bribes of both, with this condition to reſtore the money if the Cauſe went againſt them; Their Lord ignorant hereof, alwayes did impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial juſtice, whileſt his two ſerants making people pay for what was given them, by compact ſhared the money between them, which in concluſion coſt the Maſter the loſſe of his Office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29474:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Perne.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Perne</hi> Maſter of Peter houſe, and Dean of <hi>Ely</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> this Perſon was very facetious and excellent at blunt ſharp jeſts, and loved that kind of mirth even ſo as to be noted for his wit in them. This Dean chanced to call a Clergy-man fool (that indeed was little better) who replyed that he would complain thereof to the Lord Biſhop of Ely. <hi>Do ſaith the Dean when you will, and my Lord Biſhop will confirm you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet was Doctor <hi>Perne</hi> himſelfe at laſt heart-broken with a jeſt being at Court in the time of <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> with Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> his Pupil; It ſeemes he was noted to have altred his religion with the ſeveral raignes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> It fell out at his being there as aforeſaid, the Queen was diſpoſed and reſolved that afternoon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29474:16"/>for all it rained very hard, to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad contrary to the mind of her Ladies on Horſeback (Coaches not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then common) who were to attend her. Now one <hi>Clod</hi> the Queen's Jeſter was employ'd by the Courtiers to laugh the Queen out of ſo inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a journey, which he performed in this manner. Heaven quoth he Madam diſſwades you it is cold and wet, and Earth diſſwades you it is moiſt and dirty; Heaven diſſwades you, this Heavenly minded man Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> and Earth diſſwades you, your fool <hi>Clod</hi> ſuch a lump of clay as my ſelfe, And if neither will prevaile with You, here is one that is neither Heaven nor Earth, but hangs betwixt both, Doctor <hi>Perne,</hi> and he alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades you: hereat the Queen and the Courtiers laughed heartily, whilſt the Doctor withdrew himſelfe to <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and there dyed out of meer conceit of this publick dictery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29474:16"/>
               <head>Queen Elizabeth.</head>
               <p>QUeen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage, ſo that once a prime Officer with a white ſtaffe (whoſe name for his honorable Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities ſake ſhall be paſſed by) coming into her preſence, the Queen willed him to confer ſuch a place now void on one of her Servants whom ſhe commended unto him: Pleaſe your Highneſſe Madam, ſaid the Lord, the diſpoſall hereof pertaineth to me by vertue of this white ſtaſſe conferred upon me; True ſaid the Queen, yet I never gave you the office ſo abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but I ſtill reſerved my ſelfe of the <hi>Quorum;</hi> But of the <hi>Quarum</hi> Madam replied he, preſuming on her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor; hereat the Queen in ſome paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſnatching the ſtaffe out of his hand <hi>You ſhall acknowledge me, ſaid ſhe, of the</hi> Quorum Quarum Quorum, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have your ſtaffe againe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:29474:17"/>
               <head>Wood <hi>of</hi> Kent.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NIcholas Wood</hi> (I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him as a living jeſt and merriment of the times, though the greateſt grief and ſorrow to himſelf imaginable through his <hi>Caninus Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitus</hi> or doggiſh appetite) he was a Landed Man and true Labourer, he would eat proviſion for twenty men at a meal, a whole Hogg at a ſitting and at another time thirty dozen of Pigeons; this by the modern trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermen, is called playing at a bit, and ſo is rancked here in that Topick,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Biſhop Bancroft.</head>
               <p>THIS excellent Prelate was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much abuſed by virulent tongues and pens of the Puritan par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being he that managed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29474:17"/>at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> ſo learnedly and acutely; ſo that as Mithridates their venemous tongues became food to him. Once a Gentleman coming to viſit him preſented him a libell (lye becauſe falſe) bell becauſe loud) which he found poſted on his door, who nothing moved hereat, <hi>Caſt it ſaid he to an hundred more which lie here u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a heap in my Chamber.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pike.</head>
               <p>IT is known of what voracity Pikes are, being called the Tyrants of Rivers: Once a Cub-Fox drinking out of the river <hi>Arnus</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> had his head ſeized on by a mighty Pike, ſo that neither could free themſelves but were ingrapled together, in this conteſt a young man runs to the water takes them both out alive and carrieth them to the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> whoſe Palace was near thereunto. The Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would not admit him without
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29474:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>promiſing of ſharing his full halfe in what the Duke ſhould give him, To which he hopeleſs otherwiſe of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance condeſcended, The Duke high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effected with the rarity was on gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him a good reward which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refuſed, deſiring his Highneſs would appoint one of his guard to give him a hundred Laſhes that ſo the Porter might have fifty, according to his Compoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Apes.</head>
               <p>THere is a ſort of <hi>Apes</hi> in <hi>India</hi> caught by the Natives thereof in this manner, they dreſſe a little boy in his ſight and undreſſe him again lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the Childs aparell behind them and then depart a convenient diſtance: The <hi>Ape</hi> preſently atyreth himſelfe in the ſame garments till the Childs cloathes become his chains, putting of his feet by putting on his Shoos, as moſt of our Gallants doe, for <hi>French</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29474:18"/>faſhions leaving the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord William Cecill.</head>
               <p>HE was Secretary and Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 30. yeares together Anceſtor of the Earle of <hi>Exeter,</hi> being <hi>Moderator Auleae</hi> ſteering the Court at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and whileſt the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> would endure no equal, and <hi>Suſſex</hi> no Superiour therein, he by ſideing with neither ſerved himſelfe with both. Incredible was the kindneſſe which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had for him, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for her ſelfe in him, being ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that he was ſo able a Miniſter of State: coming once to viſit him, being ſick of the Gourt at <hi>Burley</hi> houſe in the Strand, and being much heightned with her head attire, (then in faſhion) the Lords ſervant who conducted her through the door, <hi>May your Highneſſe</hi> ſaid he be pleaſed to ſtoop; the Queen returned, <hi>For your Maſters ſake
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29474:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>I will</hi> ſtoop, but not for the King <hi>of Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sutton the Founder of that Hoſpital.</head>
               <p>HE got his Eſtate by being Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter at <hi>Berwick</hi> under the Queen, and by being thrifty and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in that employment, and then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned merchant. He had a merchant his Comrade, with whom he had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in common, but their charges were ſeveral to themſelves; when his friend in travel called for two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots Mr <hi>Sutton</hi> called for one, when his friend called for halfe a Pint of Wine Mr <hi>Sutton</hi> for a Gill, underſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him a moiety: at laſt Mr <hi>Sutton</hi> hearing of his Friends Death and that he left <hi>but</hi> fifty thouſand pounds Eſtate, I thought (ſaid he) he would die no rich Man who made ſuch needleſſe Expences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29474:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Kings Champion.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Robert Dimock</hi> being by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the Kings Champion at the Coronation of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. came on Horſeback into <hi>Weſtminſter Hall</hi> where the King according to cuſtome dined and caſting his Gauntlet on the ground challenged any who durſt queſtion the Kings right to the Crown. King <hi>Henry</hi> being pleaſed to diſſemble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a ſtranger to that Ceremony, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of a ſtander-by what that Knight ſaid, to whom the party re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, <hi>He challengeth any man to fight with him who dares deny your Highneſſe to be the lawfull King of</hi> England. <hi>If he will not fight with ſuch a one, ſaid the King, I will.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29474:20"/>
               <head>Sir Thomas Greſham.</head>
               <p>OSterley Houſe was built by Sir <hi>Thomas Greſham</hi> (now it is Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> where Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> entertained Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Being there Her <hi>Majeſty</hi> found fault with the Court of the Houſe as too great, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that it would appear more hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome if divided with a wall in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle: What doth Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> but in the night time ſends for workmen from <hi>London</hi> who ſo ſilently and ſpeedily followed their work that the next morning diſcovered that Court dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which the night had left ſingle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: the Queen was very well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, while a Courtier diſported her with this quibble, that it was no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he could ſo ſoon <hi>change a building who could build a Change.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29474:20"/>
               <head>Diſputation.</head>
               <p>AT an extraordinary Act of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity kept at <hi>Cambridge</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>James,</hi> when Dr. <hi>John Davenant</hi> was Anſwerer, and Dr. <hi>Richardſon</hi> amongſt others the Opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; the Queſtion was maintained in the Negative, concerning the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Kings; Dr. <hi>Richardſon</hi> vigorouſly preſſed the practice of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> excommunicating the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> inſomuch that the King in ſome paſſion returned, Truly it was moſt inſolently done by St. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> to whome Dr. <hi>Richardſon</hi> replied, This is a Majeſtick anſwer, and befitting <hi>Alexander;</hi> this is not to untie but cut the argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29474:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> John Cuts.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>John Cuts</hi> of <hi>Cambridg-ſhire</hi> was a moſt bountifull houſe-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as any of his eſtate, inſomuch that <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> in the beginning of her Reign (whileſt yet ſhe had peace with <hi>Spain</hi>) the ſickneſſe being at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> ordered the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to this Knights houſe; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour coming thither and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his name to be <hi>John Cuts,</hi> conceived himſelfe diſparaged to be ſent to one of ſo ſhort a name, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentlemen generally having voluminous names helpt and ſtuft out with Titles, uſually adding the place of their habitation for the elongation thereof. But ſoon after that the <hi>Don</hi> found that what the Knight lacked in length of name, he made up in the largneſſe of his entertainment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29474:21"/>
               <head>The Counteſſe of Shrewsbury.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAry</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> Mother of King <hi>James,</hi> being committed to the keeping of <hi>George</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> who had married a Lady of a notable, pregnant and undaunted ſpirit, the cuſtody of ſo great a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe on the Earles coſt, was quickly by her found to be chargeable, and which was worſe dangerous, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of the kingdome daily practiſing her enlargement; it hapned this Counteſſe coming to the Court, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> demanded of her how the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> did, <hi>Madam ſaid ſhe, ſhe cannot doe ill while ſhe is with my Husband, and I begin to grow jealous they are ſo great together.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Queen who liked not any familiarity of that royal Priſoner with ſo great and potent a Peer, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her removall thence into the cuſtody of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29474:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Arthur Chicheſter.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Arthur Chicheſter</hi> once Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being recalled thence, was ſent Ambaſſador to the Emperor by King <hi>James,</hi> about that labour in vain of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning thence the place where he was, the City of <hi>Maynchin,</hi> was beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Count <hi>Tilly</hi> the Emperor's Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, to whom my Lord Chicheſter ſent word that it was againſt the Law of Nations to beſiege an Ambaſſador, <hi>Tilly</hi> replyed, That he took no notice he was an Ambaſſador, the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Meſſenger, <hi>Had my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſent me with as many hundred men as he hath ſent me on fruitleſſe meſſages hither, your Generall ſhould have known that I had been as well a Souldier as an Ambaſſador.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29474:22"/>
               <head>Thomas Stukely.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas Stukely</hi> the famous <hi>Glorioſo</hi> was a younger Brother of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, wealthy and worſhipfull Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neer <hi>Ilfracombe</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> having prodigally miſpent his Patrimony, he entred on ſeverall projects, which centred in a deſigne and perſwaſion of his being a Prince. In this he was ſo confident, <hi>that be bluſhed not to tell Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>that he preferred rather to he Soveraign of a Mole-hill, then to be the higheſt Subject to the greateſt King in Chriſtendome,</hi> adding moreover, <hi>that he was aſſured he ſhould be a Prince before his death. I hope</hi> (ſaid Queen Elizabeth) <hi>I ſhall hear from you when you are ſtated in your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, I will write unto you</hi> quoth Stukely, <hi>In what language</hi> ſaid the Queen? He returned in the ſtile of Princes, <hi>To our dear Siſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29474:23"/>
               <head>Earle of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry Vere</hi> the ſeventeenth of that name Earle of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the laſt Lord Chamberlain of <hi>England</hi> of his Family, whoſe ſturdy nature would not bow to Court Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but maintain what he ſpake, came one day to the Court with a great milk white Feather about his Hat, which was then ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſuall, ſave that a perſon of his merit might make a faſhion; a Lord an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to his Family, and one whoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors were blemiſhed, ſaid in a way of jeer to him, My Lord you wear a very fair Feather; It is true, ſaid the Earl, and if you mark it, there's ne're a Taint in it. Indeed that Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve their Motto, <hi>Vero nil veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29474:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A Bite.</head>
               <p>TWO Gentlemens Servants fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, one belonging to a Courtier of great place, another to a Countrey Eſquire, fell at laſt to vye the nobleneſſe of their Maſters and their ſuperiority; ſaith the one, My maſter ſpends more in Muſtard then thine in Beef, whereunto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returned, <hi>The more ſawcy men his Followers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Richard Hackluit.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Richard Hackluit</hi> a very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable perſon, who writ that book of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voyages ſo uſefull for all Sea-Men, for which he deſerves well of this Nation; dying, left a very fair Eſtate to an unthrift Son, who embezilled it all away in a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29474:24"/>ſhamleſſe manner, vanting that be had cheated the covetous Uſurer who had given him ſpick and ſpan new mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the old land of his great great Grandfather.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Beggars Buſh.</head>
               <p>THere is a place called <hi>Beggars Buſh</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire</hi> grown into a Proverb, This is the way to <hi>Beggars Buſh;</hi> it happened that King <hi>James</hi> being in progreſſe in thoſe parts with Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, having heard that morning that my Lord had prodigiouſly rewarded a mean man for a ſmall preſent, Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>You will quickly come to</hi> Beggars Buſh, <hi>and I may even go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with you if both be ſo bountifull.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29474:24"/>
               <head>Name.</head>
               <p>ONE immoderately boaſted that there was not any of his name in all <hi>England,</hi> and yet he was a Gentleman; to whome one in the company returned, I am ſorry Sir you have never a good man of your name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Walter Rawleigh.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Walter Rawleighs</hi> firſt admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> favour, was from this occaſion; he was one day at Court, after his coming out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a very good habit (his cloaths were then a conſiderable part of his Eſtate) and there found the Queen walking, till meeting with a plaſhy place, the Queen ſcrupled to go therein; preſently <hi>Rawleigh</hi> caſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29474:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſpread his new Pluſh Cloak on the ground, whereon the Queen trod gently, rewarding him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with many ſuits for ſo free a tender of ſo fair a foot cloath; after he had attained her open favour he found many enemies (which worth never wanteth at Court) beſides cowardly detractions, of whom Sir <hi>Walter</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>If any man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth me to my face I will anſwer him with my mouth, but my taile is good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to returne an anſwer to ſuch who traduce me behind my back.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Italian</hi> Humour.</head>
               <p>LET him that will be happy for a day go to the barber, for a week marry a wife, for a moneth buy him a new horſe, for a year build him a new houſe, for all his life time be an honeſt man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29474:25"/>
               <head>Law Suit.</head>
               <p>A Lady would traverſe a Suit of Law againſt the will of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band who was contended to buy his quiet (I forbear the names both of them and the judge becauſe ſo lately done and it becomes not the perſons) by giving her her will therein though otherwiſe perſwaded in his conſcience the cauſe would goe againſt her.</p>
               <p>The Lady dwelling in the ſhire Town invited the judge to dinner (&amp; though thrifty enough of her ſelfe) treated him with very ſumptuous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. Dinner being done the judge returned to the bench where the cauſe being called, the judge gave it clearly againſt her. And when after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes in paſſion ſhe vowed never to invite judge again: Nay wife ſaid he vow never to invite a juſt judge any more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29474:26"/>
               <head>Sir Francis Cheyney.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Francis Cheyney</hi> made by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Baron of <hi>Tuddington</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> of a very ancient noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and as great and larg demeſnes &amp; Patrimony, was in his youth very wild and venturous, ſo that on a time he played at dice in his travels in the quality of an Engliſh Peer with <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France,</hi> from whom he won a Diamond of great worth at a caſt; whereupon being demanded by the King what ſhift he would have made to repair himſelfe in caſe he had loſt the caſt: <hi>I have</hi> replyed <hi>my Lord, in an hyperbolicall bravery, Sheeps Tails enough in Kent with their wool to buy a better Diamond then this.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29474:26"/>
               <head>Earle of Carnarvon.</head>
               <p>THe Earle of <hi>Carnarvon</hi> who ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly and reſolutly witneſſed his Loyalty in ſeveral fights for King <hi>Cbarles</hi> the firſt of bleſſed memory who gave him his Honour, was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded at the firſt Battel of <hi>Newbery:</hi> in his agony of death, he was deſired by a Lord to acquaint him what ſuit he would have to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> in his behalfe, the ſaid Lord promiſing to diſcharge his truſt in preſenting his requeſt and aſſuring him that his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> would be willing to gratify his deſire to the utmoſt of his power. To whom the Earle replyed, I will not dye with any ſuit in my mouth to any King ſave to the King of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29474:27"/>
               <head>Ship Money.</head>
               <p>THe begining of our late unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall broyles, was among other cauſes inputed cheifly to the impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ship-money, for which Mr <hi>Hambden</hi> was condemned in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer in a penall Sume by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of ten of the judges, who gave their opinion that that Taxe was legal, only Judge <hi>Hutton</hi> and Judge <hi>Crook</hi> declared againſt it, ſo that a ſtop was put to the levying of it, whereupon a Countryman no friend to the prerogative ſaid wittily. The <hi>King may get Ship-money by Hooke but not by Crook.</hi> but ſince that time other Taxes ten times heavyer have been taken from us by Hook and <hi>Crooke</hi> together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29474:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Coat of Arms.</head>
               <p>IT is the rule general in Armes that the playner the ancienter, and ſo conſequently the more Honourable, to this purpoſe a memorable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the beginning of whoſe Gentry might eaſily be remembred for its late riſe, was mocking at the plain <hi>coat</hi> of an ancient Eſquire, to whom the Eſquire returned <hi>I muſt be fain to wear the Coat which my Great, great, great, great, grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father left me. But had I had the happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to have bought one as you did, it ſhould have been guarded after the neweſt Faſhion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Extraction.</head>
               <p>IT happened in the raign of King <hi>James,</hi> when <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington</hi> was Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> that a Labourers ſon in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29474:28"/>that County was preſſed into the Wars being to go over with <hi>Count Mansfeild</hi> into <hi>Germany.</hi> The old man at <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> requeſted his Son might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged as being the only ſtaffe of his age who by his induſtry maintained him and his mother. The Earle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his name, which the man for a long time was loth to tell (as ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting it a fault for a poor man to confeſſe ſo proud a truth) at laſt he told his name was <hi>Haſtings, Coſen Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings ſaid the Earle we cannot all be top branches of the ſame Tree though we all ſpring from the ſame Root. your Son my Kinſman ſhall not be preſſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Complement.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman a Courtier and who had potent recommendations from King <hi>James</hi> to a Lady of Quality and Honour, to ſet off his Suit with the greateſt ſplendor, came alwayes attended with a large retinue, one
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29474:28"/>whereof was to be near his Perſon, now they were only hired for that day and ſo diſmiſt at night when he came from his wooing. This was obſerved by the Lady. One night therefore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leave of her at the ſtayre foot where his man attended him he prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſalute her as the good-night civility, to which <hi>Spare your Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſaid <hi>ſhee for probably I ſhall ſhortly ſee you again, but let me I pray you ſalute your ſervant whom I ſhall never ſee again.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>King James.</head>
               <p>KING <hi>James</hi> firſt coined his 22. ſhillings peice of Gold called <hi>Jacobuſſes</hi> where on his head he wore a Crown, after that he coined his 20. ſhillings and wore the Lawrel in ſtead of the Crown, upon which mutation <hi>Ben. Johnſon</hi> ſaid pleaſantly. That <hi>Poets</hi> being alwayes poor Bayes were rather the Embleme of Wit then wealth <hi>ſince King James no ſooner began
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29474:29"/>to wear them, but he fell two ſhillings in the pound in publique valuation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Biſhops.</head>
               <p>SOon after thoſe tumults and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Biſhops were outed illegally from their places in the Houſe of Lords, the aſſembly then ſitting at the Deanes Houſe of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> a reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop dyed, and was buried (as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it could not be obtained) by Mr <hi>Herle</hi> the Preſident of that Aſſembly, who the next day meeting with a friend of his of the Epiſcopall perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſaid unto him ſomewhat inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, <hi>laſt night I buried a Biſhop,</hi> daſhing more at his profeſſion then perſon, to whom the other returned with a like latitude to both, ſure you buried him in hop of <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> And this as to the ſacred Function and order wee ſee performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29474:29"/>
               <head>Goats.</head>
               <p>IT is known that Goats are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall brood of Wales and of great bigneſſe and are the beſt food where ſheep cannot be had: during the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by her Siſter Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the Cuſtody of Sir <hi>Henry Benefeild,</hi> ſo that none were admitted acceſſe unto her, a Goat was eſpied by a merry fellow (one of her Warders) to be walking alone with her, where upon taking the goat on his ſhoulders he in all haſt hurried him to Sir <hi>Harry.</hi> I pray (ſaid he) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine this fellow whom I found wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with her Grace, but what talke they had I know not, not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Language, he ſeems to me a ſtranger, and I believe a <hi>Welchman</hi> by his freize Coat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas ap William, ap Thomas, ap Richard, ap Howell, ap Evan, ap <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan, &amp;c.</hi> Eſquire being born of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29474:30"/>Worſhipfull parentage at <hi>Moſton</hi> in this County was empannelled of a Jury by the aforeſaid Names in the reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by the advice of the Judge his name was contracted (he conſenting to it) into <hi>Moſton</hi> the place of his Nativity and ancient Inheritance. This leading caſe was a precedent to the practice of other Gentrey in <hi>Wales</hi> who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Pedigrees at Home carry only one Sir-name abroad with them, whereby much time eſpecially in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when the dayes are ſhort, <hi>is gained for better employment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Biſhop of Glouceſter.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Goodman</hi> Biſhop <hi>Glouceſter</hi> in the raign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt when he dyed declared himſelfe by his will a Roman Catholick, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation whereof he gave at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in 1640. where he refuſed to ſubſcribe the Canons and was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29474:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore and for other Erroneous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions inpriſoned by his Brother Prelates; was wont to ſay, complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our firſt Reformers, that Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> was a very <hi>odd</hi> Man, to whom one preſently returned; He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an <hi>odd</hi> Man my Lord, for all the <hi>Popiſh</hi> party in <hi>England</hi> could not match him with his equall in learning and Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kings Porter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIlliam Evans</hi> Porter to King <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt was a <hi>Welchman</hi> of <hi>Monmouthſhire</hi> and may juſtly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a Giant for his ſtature, being full 2. yards and a halfe in height. He ſucceeded <hi>Walter Parſons,</hi> (who would take two of the biggeſt of the Guard under each arme as a liver and gizard and ſo carry them) &amp; exceeded him 2. inches in Height, but far beneath him in an equall proportion of body, for he was not only what the <hi>Latines</hi> call
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29474:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Compernis,</hi> knocking his knees toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and going out ſqualling with his feet, but alſo bandylegd a little, yet he made a ſhift to dance at an Antimaſque in Court, where he drew little <hi>Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery</hi> out of his pocket, firſt to the wonder then to the laughter of the Beholders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parſon Bull.</head>
               <p>UPON the happy and moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious reſtauration of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign to his Kingdomes one Parſon <hi>Bull</hi> a Miniſter, who had as loyally as learnedly maintained and aſſerted his <hi>Majeſties</hi> cauſe, had a benefice of ſome value conferred on him by the Kings gift, but before his Patent could be ſealed, the Lord Chancellour upon ſome preſentation had diſpoſed it, or ſome way it happened that he was hindred ſo that the Parſon had ſpent all his money in towne in attending of it; One day therefore ſeeing his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29474:31"/>grew ſhort he put his hand in his pocket and finding nothing there but the Kings Grant with his hand to it, he went confidently to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and told Him that he had loſt all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, out of his pocket and found none but his <hi>Majeſties</hi> hand therein; at which the King ſmiled and asked him if his buſineſs was not diſpatched, he repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no, Thereupon he was expreſſely recommended to the Chancellour for expedition of his Patent who at his addreſſe underſtanding him to be a wit, ſaid unto him, pray what's your name; <hi>Bull</hi> ſaid the Parſon, where are then your <hi>Hornes</hi> ſaid my Lord? if it pleaſe your Lordſhip replyed he, the <hi>Hornes alwayes go with the Hide.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Goring.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEorge</hi> Earle of <hi>Norwich</hi> Lord <hi>Goring</hi> being ſentenced by the High Court of juſtice, for that ſame crime of Loyalty with the ever Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord <hi>Capell</hi> for their moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29474:32"/>noble defence of the Town <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in 1648. was at the point of death by the potent interceſſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador reprieved from Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Duke <hi>Hambleton</hi> Earle of <hi>Holland</hi> and Lord <hi>Capell</hi> deplorably ſuffered. This Earle being viſited af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this reprieve and asked, how he did? anſwered I had thought to have pulled off my Doublet, but now I have leiſure to Hooke up my Breeches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Gentleman.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman coming to Court, as he was lighting out of his Coach, asked a Page or Lacquy that retained to ſome Perſon therein, very haſtily what a Clock it was? to whom the lad ſaid, Sir what will you give me then. The Gentleman wondering at the boy asked him what he meant by it. Sir (ſaith he) I would not have you miſtake your ſelfe. <hi>We Courtiers doe nothing without money.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29474:32"/>
               <head>Sir Henry Martin.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Henry Martin</hi> Father to the unfortunate <hi>Harry Martin</hi> (a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal in the horrid murder of the King) was a very fine Gentleman, and a very learned Perſon. By King <hi>James</hi> he was worthily advanced in the ſphere of his ſtudy the civil Lawes, wherein he was very eminent, to be <hi>Judge of the Prerogative for Probate of Wills,</hi> and alſo of the admiralty in Caſes concerning foreign traffique, ſo that as King <hi>James</hi> uſed to ſay plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, <hi>That he</hi> (Sir Henry) <hi>was a mighty Monarch in his juriſdiction over Land and Sea, the living and the dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Boots.</head>
               <p>WHen Doctor <hi>John Goſtin</hi> was laſt Vice Chancellor of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29474:33"/>being Maſter of <hi>Caius</hi> Colledge and an excellent Phyſician, it was highly penal for any Scholar to appear in Boots, it being not thought civil. Now a Scholar undertook for a ſmall wager much beneath the penalty to addreſſe himſelfe booted to the vice Chancellor, which was thought a dangerous preſumption, ſo carrying an Urinal in his hand, he craved his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for a cure of an hereditary numneſſe in his Legs, which he was fain to keep thus warm. The Doctor pittyed him, and diſmiſt him with a remedy <hi>to boot</hi> with his wager.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Gilbert Talbot.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Gilbert Talbot</hi> being made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Calis</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight upon ſome advice or ſuſpition that the <hi>French</hi> had ſome ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign upon the place by ſurpriſal, was commanded peremptorily that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently and carefully he ſhould look to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29474:33"/>his charge and <hi>fortifie</hi> the Town, to whom ſir <hi>Gilbert</hi> replyd, (being unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of neceſſaries) as briefly as bluntly, <hi>That without money he could neither</hi> fortify <hi>nor</hi> fiftify.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Robert Naunton.</head>
               <p>ONE Maſter <hi>Wiemark</hi> a wealthy Man, a great Newes-monger, and conſtant <hi>Pauls</hi> walker, hearing the newes that day of the beheading of Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> His head (ſaid he) would do very well on the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Sir <hi>Robert Naunton</hi> then Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State to King <hi>James;</hi> Theſe words were complained of, and <hi>Wiemark</hi> ſummoned to the Privy Councel, where he pleaded for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he intended no diſreſpect to Maſter Secretary, whoſe known worth was above all detraction. Only he ſpake in reference to an old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Two heads are better then one.</hi> And ſo for the preſent he was diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29474:34"/>Not long after when rich men were called on for a Contribution for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls, Wiemark</hi> at the Councel Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubſcribed a hundred pound, when Mr Secretary told Him <hi>two Hundred</hi> was better then one, which betwixt Feare and Charity <hi>Wiemark</hi> was fain to ſubſcribe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Learned Maide.</head>
               <p>A Certain learned Maid being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to King <hi>James</hi> as a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of her Sexe, for her skill in Languages, <hi>Hebrew, Greek, and Latin,</hi> beſides the <hi>French,</hi> &amp;c. which ſhe could perfectly write and ſpeak. The King without any wonderment, askt of her introducers, if ſhe <hi>could ſpin?</hi> and ſome waggiſh Courtiers anſwer'd, <hi>If it pleaſe your Majeſty, ſhe is at age to chuſe what occupation ſhe pleaſeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:29474:34"/>
               <head>Biſhopricks.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOHN WATSON</hi> Deane of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> being informed that the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> thereof being va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant would be confered on him, came to the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> the great Favourite, and privately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him two hundred pounds that he might not be made Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> but remain in his preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. The Biſhoprick being void and the Queen expreſſing her intention to confer it on <hi>Watſon,</hi> the ſaid Earle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted the Contrary, and would have uſed arguments againſt his Nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that not ſerving he was forced to tell the Queen that he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two hundred pounds to him to keep him from that dignitie, <hi>and it would be ſo much out of his</hi> way. Nay then ſaid the Queen <hi>Watſon</hi> ſhall have it, he being more worthy to have it who will <hi>give two hundred pounds to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29474:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>decline it then he that will give</hi> 2000 <hi>P. to attain it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Marſton Moor.</head>
               <p>ON that fatal day to the Royal cauſe, the Lord <hi>Goring</hi> in the begining of the Battel, which was about 3. a Clock in the afternoon <hi>July</hi> 2. 1644, having with great valour and courage routed the left wing of the <hi>Parliament</hi> Army, wherein the <hi>Scots</hi> were placed under <hi>Laſhley</hi> their Generall, who u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the rout fled a <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> mile and weabit, the lord <hi>Diddup</hi> a <hi>Scotch</hi> Baron <hi>lately made therein</hi> happened to be <hi>killed;</hi> when the account of the battel was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the king he came to be mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as a ballance to my Lord <hi>Cary</hi> eldeſt ſon of the Earle of <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſlain on the Kings ſide. At the naming of which <hi>Scotch</hi> Lord his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſaid <hi>That he hardly remembred that he had ſuch a Lord in Scotland,</hi> to which one returned <hi>That the Lord had wholly forgotten that he had ſuch a King in England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29474:35"/>
               <head>Wales.</head>
               <p>A Right worſhipfull Knight in <hi>Wales</hi> who had a fair Eſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, his rents ariſing from much barren ground, heard an Engliſhman, perhaps out of much oppoſition, to brag, that he had in <hi>England</hi> ſo much ground worth fourty ſhillings an <hi>Acre,</hi> you ſaid he <hi>have ten yardes of Velvet, and I have tenſcore yardes of Freize, I will not Exchange with you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Welch Gentleman.</head>
               <p>KING <hi>James</hi> riding late home from <hi>Theobalds</hi> to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> it happened that in the mid way it fell a raining very hard, whereupon the King who before kept a due pace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> commanded his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> neer Him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29474:36"/>to put on and make what ſpeed they could. Among the reſt there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a <hi>Welchman</hi> a retainer to the Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> but newly admitted to ſome Office and attendance on him, who by the trick or ſlighting of the Groome had a very ill Horſe put upon him. Aſſoon as the word was given, from the King the Traine flew with ſwiftneſſe and the King with them: The <hi>Welchman</hi> he ſpurred and flutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his legs to keep pace with him and with much buſle headed the party neer the Kings Perſon where he fell a belabouring his Horſe as if he were mad, the King hearing the ſtir he made, demanded who it was and what was the matter, who replyed, an't pleaſe Her Majeſty <hi>Her is as good a Shentleman as the beſt of them, but Her Cattel cannot travell ſo faſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29474:36"/>
               <head>Lord Bacon.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Parliament</hi> being called in the year 1621. <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor was outed his office for bribery, the frequent receiving whereof by him or his was plainly proved, yet for all this his taking juſt and unjuſt he was exceeding poor and much indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wherefore when motion was made in the Houſe of Commons of fineing him ſome thouſand of pounds, Sir <hi>F. S.</hi> a noble Member ſtanding up deſired that for two reaſons his Fine might be mitigated into fourty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, <hi>Firſt becauſe that would be paid, whereas a greater ſumme would only make a noiſe and never be payed,</hi> ſecondly <hi>the ſhame would be the greater, when ſuch his prodigality, that he who had been ſo large a taker in offices was reduced to ſuch penury that fourty ſhillings ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſufficient Fine for his Eſtate.</hi> So that what he got by the tryals at
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29474:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Barre as Attorney, he loſt by the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als at Barre as Chancellour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>THE ſame Sir <hi>Francis</hi> having once invited Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to his Mannour of <hi>Gorhambury</hi> a pleaſant ſeat, now in the poſſeſſion of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Sir <hi>Harbotle Grimſton</hi> Maſter of the Rolles; the Queen was much taken with the ſcituation, contrivance and beauty of the Fabrick, but as her conſtant cuſtome was to be a Critick in Architecture, told Sir <hi>Francis</hi> that the Houſe had but one fault, it was too little, to which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> replyed <hi>Madam that is not the Houſes fault, but yours who have made me the Maſter too great for it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29474:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>KING <hi>Henry</hi> being a hunting came to the Abbot of <hi>Readings</hi> Houſe to dinner (to whom ſoon after he had little or rather a big ſtomack) and found a Surloine of Beefe, then ſo named by the King ready for dinner the Abbot not knowing who he was, not gueſſing it by his ſmall retinue, bid him welcome and ſet the Beefe before him, On which the King fed heartily, while the Abbot, no nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard or unhoſpitable Preiſt merryly ſmild to ſee him lay no ſo, ſaying in a jeſt Sir I would give a hundred pounds I had as good a ſtomack, and could feed ſo, but my appetite is quite loſt: ſay you ſo thought the King, &amp; having thankt the Abbot departed; A weeke after he ſends a Purſivant to bring the Abbot up to the Councell Table, by whom without further examination he was committed to the <hi>Tower</hi> where
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29474:38"/>the King had given expreſſe order that he ſhould be kept with a very ſpare dyet, and no releife admitted beſides; this dyet ſoon brought up the Gentlemans ſtomack, ſo that he could be glad to have had a ſuffolke cheeſe and a twelfpeny loafe ſet before him: being in this way to his cure, the King appointed a Surloine to be made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and came and dined with him, where the Abbot taking him for a friendly viſitant upon the mending of his commons fed luſtily. Loe ſaith the King am not I a good Doctor, your Phyſick ſhall <hi>coſt you but</hi> 50. <hi>pounds for your Fees, the other halfe you ſhall keepe, and if ever you fall into the ſame diſeaſe, pray ſend for me. And ſo gave him his liberty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eveſham Bridge.</head>
               <p>DUring our late unnatural Warre, this <hi>Eveſham</hi> was made a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by the King, and Collonel <hi>William Leg</hi> Governour thereof, ſtorm'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29474:38"/>by Collonel <hi>Maſſey</hi> with much bravery and as well maintained. It happened in that Town one of the Garriſon Horſemen going over the Bridge while the Town was in a hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, his Horſe ſtartled, took a freake, and leapt with his rider from off the Bridge into the River, being a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fall, but coming plump down Horſe and Man over head and eares, ſwom out ſafely to the ſhore. The Gentleman ſpurs him up, and brings him to the ſame place of the Bridge again. <hi>Quoth he you did it with a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance before for your own pleaſure, you ſhall leape it again now for mine,</hi> and ſo ſpurd him over, and it pleaſed God they both came ſafe out again to the aſtoniſhment of the ſpectators.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Organs.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman would needs invite a Lady to ſee the order and beauty of the Kings Chappell, and one day
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29474:39"/>waited upon her thither: juſt as they came to the Door to enter, the Organs went, he takes her in his hand to preſſe through, <hi>no indeed Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, (holding back) I pray excuſe me, I do aſſure you I cannot dance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queen Mary.</head>
               <p>GReat hopes there were by the Papiſts that Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was with Child, nor did ſhe think other of her ſelfe, ſo that by <hi>Whitſontide</hi> it was expected ſhe ſhould be brought a bed; many Proceſſions and ſet prayers to the purpoſe were uſed, &amp; a ſolemne thanksgiving for her inpregnation: the time of her delivery thus Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, neer thereabouts a Rumor was preſently ſpread, that the Queen was delivered of a hopefull Prince, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many bonfires were made in <hi>London</hi> with ringing of Bells and ſuch like expreſſions of joy, and the like ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities were uſed ſoon after by the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29474:39"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Antwerp.</hi> In all which as there ſeemed a ſpice of madneſs, yet none was altogether ſo wild as the Curate of St <hi>Anns</hi> neer <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> who took upon him after the end of the proceſſion to deſcribe the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Child, how fair how beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull and a great Prince it was, adding <hi>The like whereof had never been ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſputation.</head>
               <p>AT the diſputation at <hi>Oxford</hi> in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Times between the Papiſts &amp; Doctor Arch Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> then diſputing for their lives, Doctor <hi>Weſton</hi> the Prolocutor opened the buſineſs in hand with this preface (you muſt know that Tranſubſtantiation was the thing to be maintained by the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts) <hi>ye are aſſembled hither brethren this day to confound that deteſtable Hereſy of</hi> the verity of the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Sacrament: this occaſioned no ſmall
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29474:40"/>ſhame in ſome, more laughter in others which was heightned by as bad a ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme in his behaviour, for during the whole time of the coutroverſy he had alwayes a cup of Wine or other good liquor ſtanding by him: when a cogent argument for their ſide which he well liked was urged, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the cup in his hand he cryed out, <hi>follow this, inſiſt upon this, this makes for us,</hi> which was ſpoken too, in as bad <hi>Latin</hi> as manners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Hunſdon.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Henry Cary</hi> of whom before was a great fauourite of Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> and who did her good ſervice, of which ſhe was no heedleſſe regarder in any of her ſubjects: It is reported of him as cheife part of his Character that his Latin and his diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and Courtſhip were alike falſe. He was deſigned Earl of <hi>Wiliſhire</hi> but the Queen for ſome reaſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29474:40"/>the inveſtiture: falling dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſick, to comfort and revive him ſhe then cauſed the Earles robes and the Patent to be brought to his bed ſide and there would have created him: <hi>No</hi> Madam <hi>ſaid the ſtout Lord, you thought me not worthy of them while I was living, and I thinke my ſelfe unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of them, now I am a dying.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>King Philip.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarles</hi> the 5. having reſigned all his hereditary Crownes and Dominions except the Empire of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> to King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond his ſon, who was by the marriage with Queen <hi>Mary</hi> the potent'ſt Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> betook himſelfe to a retired life in the Monaſtery of St <hi>Juſtus,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then ſcarce attained to the 55. year of his life to the great admiration of all the World. After which act he found himſelfe ſo abandoned by all his followers, that ſitting up late at
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29474:41"/>night in conference with <hi>Seldius</hi> his Brothers Ambaſſador, he had not a ſervant within call to light the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen down ſtayres, whereupon the Emperour took the candle into his own hands, and would needes in his own perſon performe that office, and having brought him to the top of the ſtayres, ſaid unto him, <hi>Remember Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius that thou haſt known the Emperour Charles whom thou haſt ſeen in the head of ſo many Armies reduced to ſo low a ſtate as to performe the office of an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſervant to his Brothers Minſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Terme.</head>
               <p>IN the 5. of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> 1558, there was ſuch a thin Terme that there was but one Lawyer in the Kings Bench Mr <hi>Foſter,</hi> and one Serjeant Mr <hi>Bouloiſe</hi> at the Common Pleas, both
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29474:41"/>having little more to do then to look about them, and the Judges not more to do then the Lawyers had; who in the quiet times were much increaſed, as may be gathered from the words of <hi>Heiwood</hi> the old Epigrammatiſt, and one much made of by this Queen, who being told of the great number of them, and that the multitude of them would impoveriſh the whole profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, made anſwer, <hi>No; for that alwayes the more Spaniels there were in the field, the more was the Game.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:29474:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Stumps</hi> the Clothier.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight hunting neer <hi>Malmsborough</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> (where this <hi>Tho. Stumps</hi> dwelt) in <hi>Bredon</hi> Forreſt came with all his Court Train unexpected to this Clothier, being a Man of great wealth and the greateſt Trade of cloathing in <hi>England.</hi> But great Houſe-keepers are as ſeldome ſurprized with gueſts as vigilant Captaines with enemies; for <hi>Stumps</hi> hearing thereof, commands his little Army of Workmen, which he fed daily in his Houſe, to faſt one meal until night, (which they might eaſily do without endangering their health) and with the ſame proviſion gave the King and his Court Train, (though not ſo delicious and various) moſt wholeſome and plentifull entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:29474:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Wyat.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Thomas Wyat</hi> engaging in that Rebellion of <hi>Henry Gray</hi> Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Mary</hi> upon pretence of her matching with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Popiſh Prince, being ſuſpected thereof by the Queen was warned from her, by a Herald at Armes ſent to him, to deſiſt from further intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or commotion in that buſineſſe on his allegiance, and the penalties of Treaſon and Rebellion.</p>
               <p>The Herald coming to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Houſe in <hi>Kent</hi> with his Coat Armour on his back, found it to be moated round, and the draw Bridge drawn up; whereupon eſpying a Man walking on the other ſide, he called to him; told him the haſt of his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and enquiring whether there was no paſſing over, nor ſhallowes in the place: The Man replyed yes, he might go over there; The Herald at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29474:43"/>it, was ſouced over head and eares, and his life endangered, but recovering the bank he alighted from his Horſe, and with great fury and anger came ſtorming into the Houſe (miſſing of his guide) and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the affront done him, and more to his Miſtreſſe the Queen who ſent him. Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> hearing of it proteſted his ignorance and innocence, declaring that whoſoever he ſhould name of his ſervants that did it ſhould ſuffer what puniſhment he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict: All of them being then called before him, he eſpyed the fellow, that's a Mad-man ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah ſaid the Herald, why did you ſerve me ſo? did not you tell me I might paſſe well enough over the Moat; <hi>yea,</hi> ſaid the other, <hi>for but juſt before you our Ducks that have ſhorter feet then your Horſe paſſed to and fro without any danger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29474:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> Eight.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, when he diſſolved the Monaſteries and Abbeys and other religious Houſes, had a Parliament choſen for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the old Men out of tenaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the old Religion and Clergy declining their Election, in whoſe roomes a great many young Men who had their Religion to learn from their profit and advancement, were ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in their places who carried the vote of the Country. Theſe Men did the Kings buſineſſe and devolved all thoſe great poſſeſſions and revenues of the Church into his hands: ſome diſcourſe being muttered about the rawneſſe of ſuch Councellors, and it being told the King by ſome of his privado's what the people ſaid of them, <hi>viz. That the Houſe of Commons had few or no Beards. No matter, ſaid the King, they ſhall ſit there while they have.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:29474:44"/>
               <head>King James a Hunting.</head>
               <p>KING <hi>James</hi> with ſome of his Nobles having loſt their way in a <hi>Foreſt</hi> in the perſuit of a Deer, came at laſt a hungry to the ſide of the ſame <hi>Foreſt</hi> where they eſpied a little Houſe; thither hyed the King and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded firſt what victuals in the Houſe, then with ſome comfortable leyſure the way; the good wife ſets before the King a good peice of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Beefe and a bag pudding, the King and his Followers fell to eat heartily, &amp; having contented his <hi>hoſteſs</hi> rid away: by the road ſide at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a boy preſents himſelf ſcraping with his legs, bareheaded, wheron was a thick ſcald: ſirrah ſaid the Lords, cover your head, have you never a cap? where do you dwell? In yonder cottage an't pleaſe you, (pointing to the place where the King dined) I had a Cap yeſterday, but to day my
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29474:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>mother made uſe of it for a pudding bag; Quoth the King it did me no harme in the eating, it ſhall do me leſſe in thinking of it; come put on, and let us jog it down, but it ſtirr'd the ſtomacks of his Traine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sir Henry Ruſh.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Henry Ruſh</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time had by his great expences very much impaired his eſtate almoſt to the annihilation of it, He had a Son grown to yeares and diſcretion, who ſeeing how the World went with his Father, applyed himſelfe cloſe to the ſtudy of the Law, and became a very contemplative kind of Perſon much different from the temper of his Father, who coming one day to him with ſome company, ſaid to his Son after ſome words which he hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not, what: you are muſing now, and building Caſtles in the Ayre? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed replyed the Son, <hi>I muſt build
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29474:45"/>them there or no where, for you have not left me a foot of Land to do it upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Voyage.</head>
               <p>THE Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> being to paſſe from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to <hi>Genoa</hi> in order to his Embaſſy to <hi>Rome,</hi> took <hi>Bruſchet</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> his foole along with him; as they came to be embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued <hi>Bruſchet</hi> refuſed, objecting the danger, replyed the Cardinal I have our Holy Fathers benediction in this paſſage, <hi>Oh quoth</hi> the foole <hi>I have heard the Pope had power in Heaven Earth &amp; Purgatory, but I never heard the ſee of Rome could command the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hiſpaniola.</head>
               <p>UPon the deſign of <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> in a ſecret Counſell held by <hi>Oliver
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29474:45"/>Cromwell,</hi> much debate there was upon the attempt of entrance, (as it afterwards happened betwixt the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals <hi>Venables</hi> and <hi>Pen</hi> in the iuſtant of Landing on the place) in the midſt of the diſpute up ſtood Coll. <hi>Skippon</hi> ſaith he we are differing in opinions how we ſhall get in, but heres no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe how we ſhall get out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cardinall Wolſey.</head>
               <p>CArdinall <hi>Wolſey</hi> was building him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a very coſtly and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Monument or Sepulchre, to which often reſorting to ſee how the worke went forward a fellow under the notion of a foole, ſtanding by, my <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid <hi>be you need not care how ſlowly it proceeds, for if you would uſe and occupy this grave you muſt enter in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live for it ſhall never entertaine you when dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:29474:46"/>
               <head>Ambition.</head>
               <p>GReat mens haughty enterpriſes are well caſtigated and reproved by a morall of a naturall who being of the ſcullery to King <hi>James,</hi> and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to bring the wood into the kitchin, did uſually pull out the lowermoſt billets from under the load of great ſtacks, and being asked on a time by my Lord of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> (who by chance eſpyed him a tugging of them out,) the reaſon thereof, be anſwered, he did the difficulteſt work firſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out climbing: quoth my Lord, <hi>This is a way to ſpoile a Courtier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Morall.</head>
               <p>SOme Fooles together by a river ſide put their legs into the water, when they had continued ſome time they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29474:46"/>knew not diſtinctly their own, none offering to draw them out while they were aſſured: in the interim comes a man and ſeeing them in this doubt gave them ſuch a bange about the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of their legs, that they preſently fetcht them out, being taught by the ſmart to know them. Applyable to Tyrants who in the <hi>ſtream</hi> of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity miſtake themſelves, till judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and calamity ſtrikes and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Roe.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> ſent Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to the Grand Seigniour by King <hi>James,</hi> at his Audience by the Prime Vizier, was forced to ſtand, through want of a ſeat, after his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was delivered. Whereupon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Robe or Veſt about him of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue he threw it down and upon that ſeated himſelfe, and after a little pauſe roſe up, and left it: being asked the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29474:47"/>reaſon of it by the Vizier, he ſaid that <hi>it was dishonourable for his Maſters Ambaſſador either to bring or carry ſtooles from that Court.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Poliſh Ambaſſador.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Poliſh</hi> Ambaſſador was ſent to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and as the uſe and Cuſtome of that Nation generally is to ſpeake <hi>Latine,</hi> delivered his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at a private conference in that language, the Emperour likewiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him in the ſame, but <hi>broke Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians Head</hi> a little. That the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor caught at and noted to him: the Emperour ſmiling replyed, that he had forgot he was ſpeaking with a pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogue, while he ſuppoſed him an Ambaſſador.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:29474:47"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>AT <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> betwixt the Ambaſſadors of the Emperour and the <hi>French</hi> King a quarrell aroſe for precedency in the Church whereat that time the <hi>Frank</hi> Chriſtians being all of the ſame profeſſion had one common Church; the Grand Seignior hearing of it, commanded a naked Scimiter to be hung at the door of the ſaid Church, and by his declaration ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, he would not be tyed by the cuſtome of other Princes but whoever ſpilt blood ſhould anſwer for it to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>AN Embaſſy was once ſent by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> to King <hi>James</hi> intruſted to three perſons, one who
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29474:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>had been a ſouldier his forehead was ſhot ſlanting away, another an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſo troubled with the Gout that he could ſcarce ſtand, another dull heavy fellow. <hi>Marry</hi> quoth the King <hi>here's an Embaſſy indeed, that hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Head Feet nor Heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Jerome Bowes.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Jerome Bowes</hi> was ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to <hi>Evan Vaſilowich</hi> the Tyranicall Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> from Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> it fortuned at his Arrival at <hi>Muſco</hi> he found an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour there likewiſe from the <hi>French</hi> King, who had audience appointed him the ſame day before Sir <hi>Jerome.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> according to the Europian Cuſtome in delivering his Errand put his hat on, the Tyrant without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adoe, cauſed his hat to be lightly nailed to his Head, and with no other anſwer diſmiſt him, ſoon after comes ſir <hi>Jerome</hi> and uſeth the ſame cuſtome:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:29474:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaith the Emperour knoweſt thou not what I have cauſed to be done to the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour for the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: yea replyed he, but know you likewiſe, what ever you think of him or his Maſter, dare but to touch me, I ſerve a Miſtreſs who ſhall avenge it a hundred fold upon you as ſure as your Cap is made of Furr. The Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant taken with this reſolute Anſwer ſtept to him from his Throne and took him in his Arms ſaying to his great Officers about him; <hi>you Dogs which of you would do ſo much for me,</hi> and at his departure preſented him with a Jewell, and this commendation in his anſwer and letters to the Queen, <hi>thy ſlave Jerome Bowes haſt done thee good and faithfull ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſadour or <hi>Envoy</hi> came to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Court, and being ſcard, and wounded in the face
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29474:49"/>was ſlightly lookt on by the Divan, and askt tauntingly by one of them whether his Maſter had no perſon of Honour without ſuch blemiſhes to ſend to their great Lord. To which he replyed, enough ſuch my Maſter hath, but becauſe I wear this wound before not behind am I on purpoſe ſent hither, as a teſtimony of the victory we got of you at <hi>Lepanto,</hi> where you were <hi>ſcar'd</hi> and cowardly fled, and ſo eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from being ſcard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A young Maide.</head>
               <p>A young handſome Maide belonging to my Lord <hi>Stanhop,</hi> was in Cherry time ſent by her Lady then in the Country to gather her ſome Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſuch a Tree in the Orchard. A ſervant of my Lords who infinitly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired the wench, after ſhe had by a lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der got up the Tree to the top bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, came ſneaking under her think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee her <hi>pudenda:</hi> the modeſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29474:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maide eſpying him clapt her coats cloſe about her, and bid him go off, urging him with the unhandſomeneſs of the Action: but the fellow ſtill perſiſting in his libidinous ſpeculation ſhe opened her Coats and diſcharged ſuch a ſhore of thick and thin upon his face, that the fellow was almoſt blind, and fell a rubbing his eyes, ſo that he could not find the way to the Houſe while the wench came down and ſent him a guide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Spaniſh Captain.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ROderigo de Veles</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain who had ſerved <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond in <hi>Flanders</hi> againſt the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> with good fame and repute, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing old and not able to undergo the diligence and extremity of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice retired home to <hi>Spain</hi> having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his <hi>Conge</hi> from the Acrchduke <hi>Albertus</hi> with letters of acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. With theſe upon his coming to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29474:50"/>
                  <hi>Madrid</hi> neer the Town, he unexpected and incognito meets the King, who being a hunting thereabouts had loſt his way and his Company. He comes neer and ſeeing him in the habit of a Gentleman enquires who he was, he replyes a Captain, demanded his name tells it; the King further urgeth on what occaſions he was travelling that way, he tells him that having faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerved <hi>Don Philip</hi> for ſo many yeares in the Low Countries, he came now in his old Age to ſeeke for a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereon to live the reſt of his life. Quoth the King doth his <hi>Majeſty</hi> owe you any arreares? No ſaid the Captain, why then ſuppoſe the King will not grant you a Penſion as he may refuſe, why then quoth <hi>Roderigo</hi> let the King kiſſe my Mules taile; well, ſaid the King I belong to the affaires of <hi>Flanders,</hi> come to morrow morning when the Counſell of War ſets, and I will get you admittance, ſending your name in by the doorkeeper. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly next morning he came and upon naming himſelfe as the King had
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29474:50"/>before given order, was forthwith brought into the Counſell, where he preſently found it was the King whom he had met before, <hi>Now quoth the King, Seignior Captain, what do you ſay if the King will not allow you a Penſion.</hi> Why Sir ſaid he if he will not, <hi>my Mule is ready at the Court Gate. The King highly taken with the bluntneſſe of the Man gave him in hand a good ſumme of Money and a yearly maintanance of</hi> 60. <hi>Pound per annum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Margaret Counteſs of <hi>Richmond.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Lady was Mother to <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. deſcended from <hi>John Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> a right noble and pious Lady, witneſſe her founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Cambridge</hi> peculiarly that gift of <hi>Margaret</hi> profeſſor in that univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſhe was ſo addicted to the practice of Religion and a woman of ſo humble and meeke a ſpirit, that ſhe would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29474:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſay that if the Princes of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame</hi> would joine in one league againſt the <hi>Turkes</hi> for the recovery of the Holy Land, ſhe would willingly accompany them and be their Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Aſtrologer.</head>
               <p>ONE by the Stars had foretold that <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. ſhould that year dye. This came to the Kings eare. The fellow is Complemented to the Court and brought before the King who gave him good words and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if from the Stars any thing could be told and if he had any skill in Prognoſtication; he anſwered yea; then pray tell me ſaid the King where do you think you ſhall be thoſe Holy days (Chriſtmas then approaching) here he ſtuck, and being urged he ſaid he could not tell, <hi>therefore</hi> ſaid the King <hi>I am skillfuller in this art then your ſelfe, for I know you ſhall be in the Tower, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29474:51"/>preſently commanded Him to be ſent thither.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of an unadviſed Statesman.</head>
               <p>IN the Corn-Market at <hi>Paris</hi> is a Grate or opening of the common ſhore of that City, where a privy Councellor commanded himſelfe to be buried as an expiation of ſome evil Councel he had given. The matter this. The <hi>French</hi> King was heavy and penſive for want of money. To ſupply him, he adviſed him for two yeares to lay a Gabell or Impoſt of two far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things upon ſome trifles out of the Country for two yeares only, which roſe to a great ſum. When this exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence was over the King continued the ſame Taxe, nay more by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample were laid upon the people. He ſeeing that he could not remedy this evil, not having the ſame power in diſſwading as he had in counſelling, took ſnuffe and dyed, and for a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29474:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>to all ſuch Councellors, expreſly provided in his will that he ſhould be buried in this Sink neer the place where the Toll is paid. His Sepulchre and the impoſition do yet continue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Henry the Eight.</head>
               <p>A Nobleman had killed a certain Perſon, for which fact ſome Lords of his allyance interceded with the King, and procured his pardon; it happened ſoon after the ſame Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſlew another man, and again the ſame Lords came to interpoſe, and to prevent other then their own infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, did it as ſoon almoſt as the murder was committed. Pleaſe your <hi>Majeſty</hi> (ſaith one of them) my Lord of <hi>N.</hi> hath killed a Man, but we hope— Hold there ſaid the King, 'tis not my Lord hath kill'd the Man, but 'tis the King hath done it in not ſuffering the Law to paſſe upon my Lord for the former murther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29474:52"/>
               <head>Cardinal VVoolſey.</head>
               <p>IT is known how inordinately and ambitiouſly this Prelate being then Lord Chancellor affected the Papacy, King <hi>Henry</hi> knowing the mind of the Man, reſolved to put a trick upon him; he comes therefore on a ſudden and tells him he had received an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe by his Ambaſſadour that it was queſtionleſſe that Pope <hi>Paul</hi> was dead but yet kept privately by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals in <hi>Rome,</hi> for fear of his Majeſties prevalence in the next Election. I wiſh (quoth <hi>Woolſey</hi>) ſome Perſon were choſen to that Dignity who was well affected to your Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. 'Twere well ſaid the King, what if I procured you to be elected, would your Majeſty could ſaid the Cardinal; I but (replyed the King) money is wanting; quoth the Cardinal I have three Tun of Gold by me; Give me that ſpeedily ſaid the King, I will add
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29474:53"/>the reſt of my own, which being done Newes came that Pope <hi>Paul</hi> was alive and live likely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Memorable thing.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Scot</hi> at <hi>Caſſels</hi> in <hi>Huſſia</hi> in the year 1610, but of a mean ſtature, though of wonderfull agility and ſtrength of body, lying flat on his back, having nothing but his ſhirt on, ſuſtained a ſtone of twelve pounds weight on his belly, while <hi>three Smiths</hi> with great Iron Sledges broke it all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peeces, without any harm at all done him: And alſo at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> another ſuch Perſon at the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Grand Seignior, held an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile at Armes end of 200. weight, while two luſty Smiths forged out a Horſe-ſhooe; which done he toſſed the Anvil aloft, and received it again which his armes expanded. He would break a ſteel Bow or Horſhooe with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29474:53"/>his hands without any inſtrument or help whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cardinal of Lorrain.</head>
               <p>TO gratify this Cardinal for his great paines in ſuppreſſing the <hi>Hugenots</hi> in the raign of King <hi>Francis,</hi> a meſſenger was ſent him from the <hi>Pope</hi> with the picture of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> holding her Son in her hands, drawn by the famous pencill of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Angelo.</hi> This, the Meſſenger fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſick by the way delivers to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of <hi>Luca</hi> to deliver it withall truſt and ſpeed. He having received ſome diſguſt from the Cardinal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures a peice to be drawn in <hi>Paris,</hi> of the ſame bigneſſe wherein to the life were painted the Cardinal, the Queens neece, the Queen regent, and the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> all naked, their Armes about one anothers Necks, and other laſcivious poſtures; with theſe the <hi>Luceſe</hi> comes to the Cardinal and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29474:54"/>with his letters which imparted the kind of the preſent delivers it. The Cardinal gladly accepts it: and for the Honour and more gracefull ſolemnity of this favour invites the Cardinal of <hi>Bourbon, Tournoys</hi> and <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Montpenſier</hi> to be preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſumptuous dinner at the opening of it: where to the confuſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſhame of the Cardinal this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene peice (hinting at his debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) was produced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Emperour Maximilian.</head>
               <p>THis Prince was very curious and inquiſitively critick in his Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and deſcent, a Court Paraſite to gratify the humor, told him that with ſome induſtry and with his command laid on him, he doubted not to derive him lineally (mentioning every Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by Name) from <hi>Noahs Arke.</hi> This was liſtned to, and much time was indulged to this vanity while the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:29474:54"/>ſycophant had pretty well feathered himſelfe by this device, in ſome time, ſome progreſſe (or rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trogreſſe as going backward from the top to the root) being made therein, while moſt men wondred and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently taxed this vanity but none durſt croſſe or reprove it, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Cooke who ſerved alſo as his Jeſter and with whoſe facetious quib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles he was much delighted, took him up one day in this manner. Sir it is neither Honourable nor profitable for you to enquire ſo much after the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals of your family. For now ſaith he, I as other your ſubjects do reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence your <hi>Majeſty</hi> and worſhip it as another deity, but if your Dignity be once brought to <hi>Noahs Arke,</hi> we ſhall all be kinſemen, for from thence we all Come, then farewell all your Imperiall Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:29474:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>King</hi> Charles the firſt.</head>
               <p>IT is very certainly reported, that after King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt had ſigned the Bill for the trienniall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and another, whereby he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared he would not diſſolve that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſo terribly known by the name of <hi>Long,</hi> without the conſent of both Houſes themſelves, the Earle of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> laſt deceaſed coming the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the King Bedchamber as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> was dreſſing himſelfe, ſaluted him with the Complement of good morrow Fellow Subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Generall Monke.</head>
               <p>ADmirable and ſtupendious were thoſe Actions of this renowned General towards the reſtitution of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the ſettlement of theſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29474:55"/>Kingdomes after ſuch a horrid night of Confuſions. Great was his vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, greater his prudence, but greateſt his reſervedneſſe, without all which, having to do with thoſe that had <hi>Argus</hi>'s eyes, and the old Serpents inſinuations both of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and temptation, it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to humane expectation He could ever have overcome ſuch inſuperable difficulties. It was his great ſaying and maxime, that if <hi>He thought his ſhirt knew his thoughts and intentions, he would pull it off and burn it.</hi> That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt privacy is now turned to publick glory. But I remember this paſſage alſo from the <hi>German</hi> Hiſtories to have been uſuall with <hi>George</hi> the valiant and illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Philip Landgrave of Heſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and this <hi>Landgrave</hi> were at variance and feud; it happened during the quarrel
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29474:56"/>before any rupture, three Noblemen ſubjects of the <hi>Duke</hi> being drinking hard in the <hi>Landgraves</hi> Dominions, fell a threatning what they would do to the <hi>Landgrave</hi> if they had him there, one would pull him a peeces with his nayles, the ſecond would run him through, another would give him to be torne by his Dogs: Amidſt theſe menaces, the Inne-keepers Son who was a Naturall, having over-heard what they ſaid, ſteps into their Room, and ſitting down begins his ſtory too. I have perceived (ſaith he) what you could finde in your heart to do againſt our good <hi>Landgrave,</hi> and I confeſſe they are exquiſite cruelties, but if you will liſten to me, who, if you know me not, have ſome underſtanding too, wee'l puniſh the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> and kill him in this manner, I will ſtop his mouth &amp; his noſtrils with both hands, ſo that no breath ſhall come in or out, and you with your tongues thruſt up his fundament ſhall ſhut up and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct that paſſage alſo, that no Ayre break out, which being done you will
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29474:56"/>have no need to uſe your nayles as you intended unleſſe it be to ſcratch your tongues clean. This ſpoken from one whom they knew to be a fool, ſo daſht them, that they ſneaked away and departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Fryer confeſſour.</head>
               <p>CErtain Maides came to be abſolved and confeſſe their ſins which they did with a very low voyce, it was a very ſterne Preiſt, and he more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by this low ſpeaking which might be imputable only to their modeſty, taxed them after this manner. You mumble now and ſpeak through your teeth, not opening your mouth that ſcarce a third word is audible; but when you are alone with your young men at your Wakes and Ale, you will be ſure your legs and taile too ſhall be ſtretcht wide enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:29474:57"/>
               <head>A Matron.</head>
               <p>A Grave Matron much eſteemed for her modeſty and civility, reckoned one of the prime of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Town, as ſhe came into Church through the ſnow, ſome of it ſtuck to her ſhoos and gave her ſuch a ſlip upon the free ſtones that up flew her heels and her Coats: being terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the ſuddenneſs of it, like the Thatcher falling from the Barn, ſhe rapt out two or three bawdy words ſuch as were preſumed were uſuall to her, (her tongue and her Coats diſcloſing her ſhame at once) and ſo roſe and made all confuſed haſt from her ill intended devotions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:29474:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Lyar.</head>
               <p>ONE affirmed that he had been in a certain Country, where their Bees were as big as ourſheep. This impudent lye one began to examine, &amp; therefore ſaid, ſure then the Bee-hives muſt be of a huge bigneſſe; No ſaith the other they are no bigger then ours; how then can they get in ſaid the one. This bogled the lyar like a Mouſe in pitch, at laſt, he anſwered, let them whom it concerns look to that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Benjamin Johnſon.</head>
               <p>ONE was friendly telling <hi>Benjamin Johnſon</hi> of his great and exceſſive drinking continually. Heres a grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous clutter and talk quoth <hi>Benjamin</hi> concerning my drinking, <hi>but heres not a word</hi> of <hi>that thirſt which ſo miſerably torments me day and night.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:29474:58"/>
               <head>Lewis 12th of <hi>France.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Prince had ſuffered many hardſhips, under went many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers contracted many enmities when a ſubject and Duke of <hi>Orleans;</hi> having been forced to quit his Country. At laſt by ſucceſſion the Crown devolved to him, which he prudently wore for many years being reputed one of the wiſeſt of the <hi>French</hi> Kings. Being thus ſeated in the Throne ſome Courtiers minded him now to revenge the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries he had formerly received, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the brave Prince, the injuries that were done to the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> ought not to be revenged by the King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Cavalier.</head>
               <p>A Cavalier travailing out of the Country upon the Kings returne,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29474:58"/>a foot, having a heavy leagure Cloak on his back was ſo weary with the Suns vehement heat burning through it, that he knew not what to do, at laſt within five miles of <hi>London</hi> he ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the herd of People that were travailing the ſame way, a prickeard fellow with a ſtaffe in his hand and no Coat nor Cloak; freind quoth he I am a poor Cavalier pray do me the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to lend me a Crown upon my Cloak till to morrow morning, and tell me where your lodging is and I will when I have been with my freinds come and pay you with thanks. The fellow accepts the bargain, gives him the Crown, and carries the Cloak, but as ſoon as he came to the Towns end the Gentleman returnes his Crown, takes his Cloak and with thankes for his pains departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fooliſh or litle Parliament.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLiver</hi> after the diſſolution of the long Parliament in 1653. ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29474:59"/>by an order of the Councill of Officers a little convention of a 100. and odd ſchiſmaticks, who ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Government from him, which he knew they would ſo rack and torture, that it would be thought good nature in him to take it in that afflicted condition to himſelfe. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly after they had ſat ſome four months, and playd their prankes, as before hand was ſuppoſed, he ſent Collonel <hi>White</hi> (ſince ſome of them would not agree to the reſignation of their power, as their ſpeaker and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) to turn them out. <hi>White</hi> comes with a guard of Foot, and demands the reaſon why they ſtay'd there ſince their fellow Members had given up their truſt to the Generall, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered they ſtay'd and would ſtay there a <hi>ſeeking the Lord.</hi> Puſh ſaith <hi>White</hi> that's to no <hi>purpoſe, the Lord has not been here any time theſe</hi> 12. <hi>yeares and ſo turned them out.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:29474:59"/>
               <head>Peter Houſe in Cambridge.</head>
               <p>ONe Miſtreſs <hi>Mary Dale</hi> of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> for ſome reaſons was a very af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate benefactour to <hi>Peter-Houſe</hi> in Cambridge, ſhe founded two fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips and two Scollarſhips there, and proffered more if on her termes it it might be accepted. For ſhe would have ſetled Lands on that houſe to the value of 500. <hi>Pounds per annum,</hi> on condition it ſhould be called the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi> This, Doctor <hi>Soams</hi> then Maſter of the Houſe refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, affirming that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> who ſo long had lived ſingle, was now too old to have a <hi>Feminine Partner.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Count Maurice of <hi>Naſſau</hi> and <hi>Spinola.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall being invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to an entertainment by the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:29474:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>aforſaid Prince at <hi>Breda</hi> ſoon after the publication of the twelve years truce, when Lemons and Oranges were brought in for ſauce at the firſt courſe, what a brave Country quoth <hi>Spinola</hi> is my Maſters affording this fair fruit all the year long. But when Cream was brought up to cloſe the feaſt Grave <hi>Maurice</hi> returned, <hi>what a brave Country is ours that yeeldeth this fruit twice every day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Coward.</head>
               <p>THere was a Souldier that vaunted before his Commander, of the hurts and wounds he had received in his face: His Captain well knowing of him to be but a Coward told him, <hi>you were beſt take heed next time you run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way how you look back.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:29474:60"/>
               <head>Goldſmith Hall.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman that had been ruined with his compoſition at <hi>Goldſmith-Hall</hi> being met by a Country man of his acquaintance, was asked by him how he lived in thoſe times? replyed the other no way diſmayed with his fortune, <hi>I live like a Prince,</hi> I do not know quoth the other what you mean by that, why ſaith the other <hi>I eate and drinke and owe much money.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Count Gundomar.</head>
               <p>HIS Embaſſy hither was much maligned by the meaner ſort, being about the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Match of which without the reſtitution of the Palatinate they were not deſirous; hereupon there was an order made by Proclamation that men ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:29474:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>to <hi>meddle with matters of State</hi> and confine their diſcourſes to their private Concerns: it happened that <hi>Gundomar</hi> coming up <hi>Ludgate</hi> hill in a Sedan, one of the Porters caſually fell and overturned the Sedan into the kinnel, where the <hi>Count</hi> ſhut up called out for help. No quoth a ſtander by let him lye there, ther's a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>we muſt not meddle with State matters.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Moor.</head>
               <p>HAD only Daughters at the firſt one of whom at the laſt was of a very remarkable piety towards him, and his wife did ever pray for a boy. At laſt ſhe obtained her wiſh, the boy coming to mans eſtate proved but ſimple, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> thereupon ſaid to his wife <hi>thou prayeſt ſo long for a boy that he will be a boy as long as he lives.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:29474:61"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> on the day he was beheaded had a Barber ſent to him becauſe his Beard and hear of his head was grown very long, which was thought at Court would tender him the greater object of pity to the people. The Barber accordingly came and asked him whether he would be pleaſed to be trim'd. In good faith honeſt fellow ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas, the King and I have a Suit for my head, and till the Title be cleared I will be at no coſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Again.</head>
               <p>THE ſame Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> when Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> had ſent him by a ſuiter in Chancery two ſilver Flagons. When they were preſented
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29474:62"/>by the Gentlemans ſervant, he ſaid to one of his Men have him to the Celler, and let him have of my beſt Wine and turning to the ſervant ſaid <hi>Tell thy Maſter if he like it let him not ſpare it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Courtiers.</head>
               <p>IT is an old Adage that Princes Privados and Favourites of Kings were like caſting Counters, which are uſed in the Exchequer as in play to count by. That ſometimes they ſtand for one, ſometimes for ten, ſometimes for a hundred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>IT is reported of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight that diſguiſing himſelfe in a mean habit he aſſociated himſelfe among ſome good fellowes, in purpoſe to know what the people thought and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29474:62"/>ſaid of him. One of the company ſpoke ſomething freely of him, giving him a character which the King knew was not much out of the way. Whome the King as a wary Concellour advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to make diſcourſes of Princes. For if he ſhould prayſe them he ſhould lye: and if he diſprayſed them he brought himſelfe into danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Chancellor <hi>Hatton.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN his time when the Councellours of two Parties ſet forth the Limits and Boundaries of the Land in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Plat; And the Councell of one part ſaid <hi>we lye on this ſide my Lord,</hi> and the Councell of the other part ſaid <hi>and we lye on this ſide:</hi> The Lord Chancellor aroſe and ſaid. <hi>If you lye on both ſides whom will you have me to beleive?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:29474:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Richardſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Dilatory ſuit had been ſome time depending in the Kings Bench be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, which the Plaintiffe could not bring to tryall, at laſt he obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a peremptory day, the Deſendant moved again, &amp; for ſome reaſons ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deſired a longer day; 'Twas in <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Terme,</hi> quoth Judge Richardſon, <hi>you ſhall have the longeſt the Court can grant, take the 11th of June, Saint Barnabies day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Philip the Second.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Portugall,</hi> he gave ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge to his Leiutenant that the Souldiers ſhould not ſpoile, leſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the hearts of the people ſhould be alienated: it came by this meanes to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29474:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſſe that the Army ſuffered much want of victuall. Whereupon the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Souldiers thereafter uſed to ſay. That they had won the King a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on Earth as the Kingdome of Heaven uſeth to be won, <hi>by faſting and abſtaining from that which is another Mans.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Courtier in Debt.</head>
               <p>THere was a Courtier that dyed greatly in debt, when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his death came to ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany (where divers of his Creditors uſually met) that he was dead, one began to ſay, Well if he be gone then he hath carried 500 <hi>l.</hi> of mine with him into the other World, and another ſaid 200 <hi>l.</hi> of mine, and a third ſpake of great ſums of his. Whereupon one that was amongſt them ſaid, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive now that though a man cannot carry any of his own with him into
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:29474:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>the other World, yet he may carry away that which is another mans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman who had a debt due from a Lord lately returned into <hi>England</hi> by Bond, came to him and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted his Lordſhip with it, who referred him to his Steward or Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; at his Addreſſe to him he looks upon the Bond, and ſeeing it to be of an old ſtanding, ever ſince 40. quoth he ſir I have nothing to ſay to this, this is an old debt, replyed the other in a little heat, <hi>hath your Lord contracted any new ones? I thought there had been no more mad Men in</hi> England <hi>to have truſted them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:29474:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>In the Land of <hi>Hiſpaniola.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UPon the landing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army upon that place, Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was made that no man ſhould plunder or take any Plate, Bullion or Jewels upon pain of death: the thirſt and heat of travell did not more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and diminiſh their ſtrength then the Proclamation abated their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſo that one merrier then the reſt after their defeat, ſaid, <hi>the General had done well to have prohibited their ſtripping the naked</hi> Molattos <hi>of their Breeches and Doublets alſo when they ſhould fall into their hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parliament Coyne.</head>
               <p>A Country honeſt fellow upon the firſt coming out of that money, taking it in his hand and turning it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29474:65"/>backward and forward when he had read the circumſcription of it, ſaid, Here are croſſes enough I trow me, but how long they ſhall laſt I know not, for I ſee here the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>God with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> are not of one ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Treaſurer.</head>
               <p>WHen my Lord came firſt to be Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> he complained to the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon</hi> of the troubleſomneſſe of the place for that the Exchequer was ſo empty: The Lord Chancellor anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, my Lord be of good cheer, for now you ſhall ſee the <hi>Bottom</hi> of your buſineſſe at the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:29474:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Preſent.</head>
               <p>WHen peace was renewed with the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> divers of the great Counſellors were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from the <hi>French</hi> with Jewels, The Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi> being then a Privy Counſellor was omitted, whereupon the King ſaid to him, my Lord how happens it that you have not a Jewell as the reſt, my Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered according to the Fable in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, non ſum Gallus ideoque non reperi Gemmam.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lord Bacon.</head>
               <p>WHen Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> was made the Kings Attorney, Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> was put from being Lord Chiefe Juſtice of the common Pleas to that of the Kings Bench,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29474:66"/>which was obſerved before as a place above it in dignity, below it in profit. My Lord <hi>Coke</hi> meeting with Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> Maſter Atturney, (ſaith he) this change is all your doing, it is you that have made this ſtir. My Lord, replyed he, <hi>your Lordſhip hath all this while grown in</hi> bredth, <hi>you muſt needs now grow in</hi> height, <hi>or elſe you would be a Monſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Judge Popham.</head>
               <p>MAſter Sarjeant <hi>Popham,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Lord Chiefe Juſtice <hi>Popham,</hi> (who ſaid he would make the Road ſo ſafe that a man might travell with a white Wand in his hand, and performed his word) when he was choſen Speaker of the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> who had ſate long &amp; done nothing in effect, coming one day to Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> ſhe ſaid unto him; Now Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Speaker what hath paſſed in the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29474:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>Houſe of Commons, He anſwered, <hi>if it pleaſe your Majeſty ſeven weekes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pace.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAce</hi> the bitter and tart fool was not ſuffered to come at Queen <hi>Elisabeth</hi> becauſe of his bitter humor; yet at one time ſome perſwaded the Queen to admit him, undertaking for him that he ſhould keep within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe: ſo he was brought to her, and the Queen ſaid come on <hi>Pace,</hi> now we ſhall hear of all our faults; quoth <hi>Pace,</hi> I do not uſe to talke of that which all the Town talkes of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Biſhop Latimer.</head>
               <p>BIſhop <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaid in a ſermon at Court, that he heard great ſpeech that the King was poor, and many wayes were propounded to make him rich. For his part he had
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29474:67"/>thought of one way which was that they ſhould help the King to ſome good Office, for all his Officers were very rich.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mendoza.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MEndoza</hi> that was viceroy of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru</hi> was wont to ſay that the Government of <hi>Peru</hi> was the beſt place the King of <hi>Spain</hi> gave, ſave that it was too near <hi>Madrid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Country man.</head>
               <p>A Certain Countryman being at an Aſſizes and ſeeing the Priſoners holding up their hands at the Barr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to ſome of his acquaintance, that the Judges were good for tune tellers, For if they did but look upon a mans hand they could tell whether he ſhould live or dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:29474:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Purſivant.</head>
               <p>THere was a <hi>Purſivant</hi> had lodged a Gentleman in a very ill Room who expoſtulated with him ſomewhat rudely; But the <hi>Purſivant</hi> careleſſely replyed, you will take pleaſure in it when you are out of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Admiralty.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Giles Merrick</hi> a landed Man in the <hi>Bermudas</hi> was ſaying that his great Grandfather, grandfather, and Father, died at Sea: ſaid another that heard him, And I were as you I would never come at Sea, why quoth the other, where did your great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and grandfather, and Father dye, he anſwered, where but in their beds? he returned, and I were as you I would never come in bed again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:29474:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Bacon.</head>
               <p>WHile Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> the Lord Keeper lived, every room in <hi>Gorhambury</hi> was ſerved with a Pipe of water from the ponds diſtant about a mile from thence, ſoon after during the habitation of Maſter <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Bacon</hi> the eldeſt Son of Sir <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> in the ſame Houſe, the water ceaſed. Maſter <hi>Anthony</hi> dying, and my Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> inheriting it, the water could not be recovered without great charge. Being made Lord Chancellor he thereupon built <hi>Verulam</hi> Houſe cloſe by the pond yard for a place of receſſe and privacy when he was to do any important buſineſs, being one time asked <hi>why he built that Houſe there</hi> he anſwered, that ſince he could not carry the water to his Houſe, he would carry his Houſe to the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:29474:68"/>
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>A Lady walking with Mr <hi>Bacon</hi> in in <hi>Grayes Inne walkes</hi> asked him whoſe, that peice of ground lying <hi>next under the walls was,</hi> he anſwered theirs. Then ſhe asked him if thoſe feilds beyond the walkes were theirs too, he anſwered, yes Madam thoſe are ours as you are ours to look on and no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Bacon.</head>
               <p>WHen Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> was newly advanced to the great ſeal <hi>Count Gondamor</hi> came to viſit him, and to complement him on the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor confer'd on him my Lord reply'd, That he was to thank God and the King for that Dignity, but yet ſo he might be rid of the burden he could
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:29474:69"/>very willingly forbear the Honour, and that he formerly had a deſire and the ſame continued with him ſtill to lead a private life, <hi>Count Gondomar</hi> replyed, I will tell your Lordſhip a Tale of an old Rat <hi>that would needs leave the world and therewith acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the young Rats that he would retire into his Hole and ſpend his dayes ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and would enjoy no more comfort, commanding them upon his high diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure not to offer to come in unto him. In obedience to this command they forbare</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>dayes, at laſt one that was more hardy then the reſt incited ſome of his fellowes to go in with him and he would venture to ſee how his Father did, for he might be dead, They accordingly went in, and found the old Rat ſitting in the midſt of a rich Parmezan Cheeſe; my Lord laughed, but his neceſſityes after that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment agreed not with the Fable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:29474:69"/>
               <head>Lord Henry Howard.</head>
               <p>IN the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> when the diſtreſſed Eſtates of <hi>Holland</hi> ſupplicated the Queen for aſſiſtance, there came one Agent from them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Caroon, and when he had often moved the Queen for further ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours and more Men, my Lord <hi>Henry Howard</hi> jeſted upon him thus, <hi>That he agreed well the name of Charon Ferry man of Hell, for he came ſtill for more men to encreaſe Regnum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrarum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Fulke Grevil Lord Brook.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Fulke Grevil</hi> being then a Member of the Houſe of Commons, when that Houſe in a great buſineſs &amp; large debate ſtood much upon Precedents ſaid unto them, <hi>why do you ſtand ſo much upon Precedents? The times hereafter
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:29474:70"/>will</hi> be good or bad; if good, prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents will do no harm, if bad, power will make a way where it findes none.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Affected Gravity.</head>
               <p>MAny men eſpecially ſuch as affect Gravity have a manner after other mens ſpeech to ſhake their head, A principall officer of this Land uſed to ſay, it was as men ſhake a bottle to ſee if there were any wit in their Heads or no.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury,</head>
               <p>IN diſcourſe of the Puritans and non conformiſts of the times, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to a greater meaſure of piety and ſanctity, this Arch-Biſhop reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That ſome hypocrites and ſeeming mortyfied men which held down their
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:29474:70"/>Heads were like the little Images in the Vaults or Roofs of Churches which look and bow</hi> down as if they <hi>held</hi> up the Church when as they bear no weight at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Tilting.</head>
               <p>IN Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time when Tilt and Tourney and running at the ring was much in Faſhion, there came a Gentleman all in Orange tawney and ran very ill, the next day he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain all in Green and ran worſe, there was one of the lookers on asked ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what is the reaſon that this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman changeth his colours, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwered I thinke becauſe <hi>it may be reported that the Gentleman in the Green ran worſe then the Gentleman in the Orange Tawney.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:29474:71"/>
               <head>Sultan Selymus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltan Selymus</hi> was the firſt of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperours that did ſhave his beard as <hi>Busbequius</hi> reports, whereas his Predeceſſors wore it long: one of his Baſhawes therefore asked him the queſtion, why he altered the cuſtome of his progenitors, he reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe you Baſhawes ſhall not lead meby the beard as you did them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conſalvo the great Captain.</head>
               <p>AFter a great fight there came to the Camp of <hi>Conſalvo</hi> the great Captain, a Gentleman, proudly horſed and armed, another <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captain asked <hi>Conſalvo</hi> who that Gentleman was, who anſwered, <hi>It is Saint Ermin who never appeares but after the ſtorm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:29474:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Wotton.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>UPon conſideration of thoſe many panegyricks and laudatory ſpeeches, letters and exhortations to great men, he once ſaid, that</hi> though the manner of Painters be to mend the picture by the life, yet with generous minded men it ſhould be inverted, viz. to mend the life by the picture, to become ſuch as thoſe encomiums expreſſe a man to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Buſineſſe.</head>
               <p>IT was uſuall ſaying of my Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> that it was in buſineſſe as it is frequently in wayes, that the next and neereſt way is commonly the fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, and that if a man will go the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way he muſt go ſomewhat about.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:29474:72"/>
               <head>Robert Earle of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Earle was the greateſt Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite and ſubtle enemy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> much voyced up by the non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, for his patronage of them, whereby he drew that faction clearly to his ſide, he was alwayes very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtfull and jealous, and ſad examples there were of his treachery, and it was his uſuall ſaying that we read that we ought to forgive our enemies, but we do not read that we ought to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Earle of Eſſex.</head>
               <p>IT was uſually ſaid of <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> the Father of the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed and who was altogether as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and popular (and I remember an obſervation made that when the Son departed from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Barnet</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:29474:72"/>and ſo onward againſt the King, it was bruited, that with the ſame Pomp his father began his expedition the ſame road to <hi>Ireland</hi> and ſoon after loſt his Head which fate was ſuſpected to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Son, though a potion its thought did the ſame effect) that he <hi>was the the greateſt uſurer in England for that he had turned all his Eſtate</hi> (<hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving waſted a great part thereof in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall voyages</hi> and expeditions by careſſing the the ſouldiers) <hi>into obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Caeſar Borgia.</head>
               <p>THe ſuppoſed Nephew but ſon of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth one of the worſt of that ſee, yet ſo great a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor to the family of this preſent Pope, that he hath aſſumed his name by the name of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſeventh: after long diviſion betwixt him and the Eſtates of <hi>Romania,</hi> came to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with them: in the Treaty
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:29474:73"/>there was an article that he ſhould not call them at any time altogether in perſon. Their intention was that knowing his treacherous and cruel na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture if he meant them any danger or treaſon he might not have the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity or advantage to oppreſſe them altogether at once. Notwithſtanding he brought it ſo about by his fineſſes and artifices that he won upon their confidence to aſſemble together at <hi>Cinigalia</hi> where he murthered them all. The newes hereof was related to the Pope as a thing perfidious but happy, who upon hearing of it ſaid, It was they that <hi>had broke their Covenant firſt in coming altogether.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Court Maxim.</head>
               <p>IT is fathered on the Emperour <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan,</hi> who uſed in ſpeaking of the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy of Princes, that ſeek to make away thoſe that aſpire to the ſuccceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there was never King that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:29474:73"/>did put to death his ſucceſſor; this was very rife in the buſineſſe of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> beheaded by Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sir Nicholas Bacon.</head>
               <p>THis Knight was Sir <hi>William Cecils</hi> ſecond in the ſervice of the <hi>State</hi> being Father alſo to my Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> and Lord Chancellour in the raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> upon bills exhibited in that Court to diſcover where Lands lay, upon proofe that they had a certain quantity of Land but could not ſet it forth, was wont to ſay, <hi>and if you cannot finde your Land in the Country, how will you have me find it in the Chancery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:29474:74"/>
               <head>Conbury Park.</head>
               <p>THe Earle of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Favorrite to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was making a large chace about <hi>Cornbury</hi> Parke, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to encloſe it with poſts and Rayles, and one day was caſting up his charge what it would come to, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſtanding by that was a free ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man, ſaid to my Lord upon the ſudden, <hi>methinkes your Lordſhip goeth not the cheapeſt way to worke, why Sir ſaid my Lord, Introth my Lord ſaid he count you but upon the poſts for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try will find you Rayling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Knights.</head>
               <p>MY Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded at the Seige of <hi>Rhoan</hi> an Army of <hi>Engliſh</hi> in ayd of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. of <hi>France</hi> againſt the league,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:29474:74"/>made 24. Knights (after a battel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duke <hi>de Main</hi>) which at that time was a great number, divers of thoſe Gentlemen were of weake and ſmall means which when Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> heard, ſhe ſaid <hi>my Lord might have done well to have built his Almes houſe before he made his Knights.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>French Maſſacre.</head>
               <p>AFter the Maſſacre of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, in <hi>Paris,</hi> on S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomews</hi> day an overture was made of a new agreement, to that purpoſe the Deputies of the reformed Religion met there to treat of a Pacification, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome debate they agreed on arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, nothing remaining but the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the performance of them, to this the Queen mother returned by way of queſtion, whether they would not accept the Kings ſecurity, no by St <hi>BARTHOLOMEW</hi> Madam anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Deputies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:29474:75"/>
               <head>Treaſure.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour coming to <hi>Venice,</hi> was there Complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the State and as a particular Honour to himſelfe and his Maſter had St. <hi>Markes</hi> Treaſure, reckoned then to be the greateſt magazine of wealth in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhewed him, At the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame he pointed towards the great Cheſts and asked ſome of the ſenators, whether thoſe Iron-coffers had any bottome, they anſwered yea, this is nothing then ſaith he to my Maſters wealth, that hath a perpetuall ſpring in his Mines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Retinue.</head>
               <p>A Nobleman, who kept a very large retinue, was acquainted by his Steward, that great part of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:29474:75"/>was very burdenſome and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for that his Lordſhip needed not ſo many ſervants, wherupon he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Steward to bring him a liſt and Catalogue of all his ſervants, and to mark their names w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the frugall ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard did putting out by his note above halfe his retainers. When this ſcroll was preſented the Nobleman asked what he marked ſo many out for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sir ſaith he they are of no uſe to you; why then ſaith the Lord <hi>if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt ſtay becauſe I have need of them, theſe ſhall ſtay becauſe they have need of me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</head>
               <p>HEnry the fourth of <hi>France</hi> after he had marryed <hi>Mary de Medicis</hi> was for a little while childleſſe, upon newes of the Queens conception, the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> who was heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Crown, gave out, that it was with a pillow: theſe words came
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:29474:76"/>to the Kings ear, who, the Queen gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing very big, tooke the ſaid <hi>Count</hi> to her lodgings and laid his hand upon her Apron, what think you now Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen quoth the King of this pillow, marry ſaid the <hi>Count I think it to be a Pillow for all France to reſt its head upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proud Prelate.</head>
               <p>A Proud Prelate of <hi>England</hi> in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his great example the Pope, would admit no ſuitors in any other poſture but proſtration: a man reputed for his wiſedome petitioning of him was forced to comply with the cuſtome, being taxed by ſome for this ſervile flattery as unbecoming men to no greater a perſon then a Biſhop, he anſwered, <hi>that it was none of his fault, but the Prelat's who carried his eares in his Feet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:29474:76"/>
               <head>Lord Wentworth.</head>
               <p>AFter my Lord <hi>Wentworth</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor to the Earle of <hi>Cleveland</hi> had loſt <hi>Calice,</hi> through want of a ſufficient Garriſon being forced on a ſudden by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, who had failed of another great enterpriſe on <hi>Naples</hi> the Queen never dawed day but with the complaints of <hi>(Quintili redde legiones)</hi> render me <hi>Calice,</hi> quite ſpent her ſelfe; the Lord Chamberlain delivering her one night the Key ſhe ſighed and ſaid, <hi>this is not the key of Calice:</hi> which was alwayes held for the Key of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Earle of Dorſet.</head>
               <p>ONE Captain <hi>Beale</hi> ſerved my Lord with hats, which he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at high and exceſſive rates, my
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:29474:77"/>Lord underſtanding by his Steward the rate of his bills ſent for his Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſher, Sir quoth my Lord, what is your meaning to ſet me ſuch prizes in which there is no conſcience, why my Lord quoth Captain <hi>Beale,</hi> we citizens muſt ballance accounts, if you do not pay me then you cheat me, but if you do then I cheat your Lordſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The grand Seignour.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DON John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> was Generall at the fight of <hi>Lepanto</hi> againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> where he gave them a ſignall overthrow, this being related to the Grand <hi>Seigniour,</hi> who had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken the whole Kingdome of <hi>Cyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> from the <hi>Venetians</hi> he contentedly ſaid, that the loſſe of a Fleet to him was but as the ſhaving of his beard which would grow again, but the loſſe of a Kingdom was like the lopping off a member.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:29474:77"/>
               <head>Philip the ſecond of Spain.</head>
               <p>HE was of ſo rare a temper that after his invincible Armado was defeated upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſts, and diſperſed with winds driven about the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> back again; upon the newes thereof he only ſaid that he ſent not out that Fleet to fight againſt the <hi>Windes:</hi> Another time having writ expreſſes to <hi>Flanders</hi> when they were fairly copyed he gave them to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to throw ſand upon them, who miſtaking the box throw'd Ink in ſtead of it and wholly defaced them, he ſaid no more but went into his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and tranſcribed them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colonel Maſſey.</head>
               <p>IT is commonly reported that at the ſeige of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> before the Citizens burnt down the ſuburbs, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:29474:78"/>the King had ſummoned it, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> ſent word to the Governour that if he yeilded not preſently he would forthwith fire him out, to which Collonel <hi>Maſſey</hi> returned, let the Prince do ſo and I will meet and fight with him in the Flame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lady Lambert.</head>
               <p>MUch talke there was of ſome familiarity betwixt <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> and my Lady <hi>Lambert,</hi> upon the device of the <hi>Inſtrument of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which was cheifly aſſiſted by <hi>Lambert</hi> upon mutuall aſſurances that he ſhould ſucceed in the protectorſhip when that project took effect in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1653, it was ſaid by a wag that <hi>Olivers Inſtrument was found in my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Lamberts Placket.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:29474:78"/>
               <head>Olivers Commiſſioners of the Treaſury.</head>
               <p>THere was a great complaint of money (as occaſion enough) in the publique receits as they called them: in that Parliament which was called in 1656, great ſtir was made for a ſupply, among the reſt an Act was propounded for the better regulation of the Exchequer, which ſome finger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of that money (as moſt of them were ſuch) would have only to look forward to the future management of it, ſaith <hi>Thurloe</hi> the Secretary, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, if a man hath loſt his purſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould he look backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; my Lord hath loſt his <hi>Purſe</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:29474:79"/>
               <head>Harry Marten.</head>
               <p>THis Antimonarchical Perſon being condemned for the execrable murther of King <hi>Charles,</hi> was after ſentence (he coming in upon the Kings Proclamation) brought before the Houſe of Lords to ſhew cauſe why he ſhould not ſuffer due execution of his judgement, to which he returned anſwer, that true it was he could not nor did expect any favour from that Houſe, whoſe extirpation he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavorured and as to the <hi>King, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged he never had obſerved any of his or his predeceſſors Proclamations ſave one, and for that he ſhould be hanged.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:29474:79"/>
               <head>Lord Bruce.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Edward Sackvile</hi> afterwards Lord <hi>Dorſet</hi> was challenged by this Lord to fight with him in the low Countreys upon ſome fend betwixt them, in the duel they were both grievouſly wounded, yet would not give over: at laſt it was my Lord <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets</hi> fortune to throw him upon a cloſe and having him at this advantage prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him his life, <hi>no quoth the</hi> Scotch <hi>Lord I ſcorne to accept it at the hands of an</hi> Engliſh <hi>man, and I then ſcorne ſaith Dorſet to give it to a</hi> Scotch <hi>man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Monſiure Bellieure.</head>
               <p>WHen the King was in the hands of the <hi>Scotch</hi> at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and bargained and ſold by them to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> this Monſiure being the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:29474:80"/>
                  <hi>French</hi> Kings Ambaſſadour came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeeing the ſale agreed upon departed, at his going away <hi>Laſhley</hi> ſent a Guard of horſe to bring him into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Quarters, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived he called for the Corporall of the ſquadron, and having a halfe Crown in his hand demanded of him what that peice was, thirty pence Sir ſaid he, <hi>even for ſo much the</hi> Jewes <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed our Saviour take, this among you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:80"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE NAMES OF Thoſe PERSONS in theſe <hi>Collections.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Folio.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>HEnry the <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Queen Elizabeth.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Hunſden.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Treaſurer.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord cheife Juſtice.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>5</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>King Wardrope.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>6</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shoomaker no Gentleman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:81"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir William Clarke</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>8</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Spencer.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>9</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doctor Preſton.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>10</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Thomas Moor.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>11</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Horatio Pollavieini.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>14</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doctor Perne.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>15</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Queen Elizabeth.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wood of Kent.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhop Bancroft,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Pike.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Apes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord William Ceeil.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Maſter Sutton the founder of that Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>22</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Robert Dymock the Kings Champion.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>23</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Thomas Greſham.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>24</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cambridge Diſputation.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>25</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir John Cutts.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>26</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Counteſſe of Shrewſebury.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>27</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Arthur Chicheſter.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>28</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thomas Stukely.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>29</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Earle of Oxford.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>30</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Bite.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>31</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Maſter Richard Hackluit.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:81"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beggars Buſh.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>32</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Name.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>33</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Walter Rawleigh.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An Italian Humor</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>34</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Law Suit.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>35</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Francis Cheney.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>36</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Earle of Carnarvon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>37</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shipmoney.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>38</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Coat of Armes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>39</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Extraction.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Complement.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>40</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>King James.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>41</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhops.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>42</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Welchmen.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>43</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhop Glouceſter.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>44</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Kings Porter.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>45</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Parſon Bull.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>46</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Goring.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>47</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gentleman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>48</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Henry Marten.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>49</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Boots.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Gilbert Talbot.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>50</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Robert Naunton.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>51</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Learned Maide.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>52</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhopricks.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>53</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:82"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marſton Moore.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>54</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wales.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>55</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Welch Gentleman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>57</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>58</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry the <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>59</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eveſham Bridge</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>60.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Organs.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>61.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Queen Mary.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>62</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Diſputation.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>63</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Hunſdon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>64</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>King Philip.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>65</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Terme.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>66</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Stumps the Clothier.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>68</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Thomas Wyat.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>69</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry the <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>71</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>King James a hunting.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>72</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Henry Ruſh.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>73</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Voyage.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>74</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hispaniola.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cardinal Wolſey.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>75</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ambition.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>76</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A moral.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Thomas Roe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>77</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Poliſh Ambaſſadour.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>78</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>79</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:82"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sr. Jerome Bowes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>80</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>81</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A young Maide.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>82</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Spaniſh Captain.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>83</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Margaret Counteſſe of <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>85</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An Aſtrologer.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>86</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An unadviſed Statesman.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>87</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry the <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>88</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cardinal Wolſey.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>89</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A memorable thing.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>90</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Cardinal of Lorrain.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>91</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Emperour Maximilian.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>92</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>King Charles the firſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>94</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Generall Monke.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Philip Landgrave of Heſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>95</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Fryar confeſſour.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>97</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Matron.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>98</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Lyar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>99</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ben. Johnſon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lewis the <hi>12</hi> of France.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>100</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Cavalier.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The little or fooliſh Parliament.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>101</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Peter Houſe in Cambridge.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>103</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Count Maurice of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and <hi>Spinola.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:83"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Coward.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>104</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Goldſmiths Hall.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>105</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Count Gundomar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Thomas Moore.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>106</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>107</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Again.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Courtiers.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>108</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry the <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Chancellor Hatton.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>109</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Cheife Juſtice Richardſon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>110</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Philip the ſecond.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Courtier in Debt,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>111</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>112</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hispaniola.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>113</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Parliament Coine,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Treaſurer.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>114</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A preſent.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>115</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Judge Popham.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>116</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pace the Fooll.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>117</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhop Latimer.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mendoza.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>118</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Country man at Aſſizes.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Purſivant.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>119</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Admiralty.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Francis Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>120</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:83"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Another.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>121</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Francis Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Henry Howard.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>123</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Fulke Grevil Lord Brook.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Aſſected Gravity.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>124</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Arch Biſhop of Canterbury.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Tilting.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>125</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sultan Selymus.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>126</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Conſalvo the Great Captain.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Henry Wotton.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>127</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Buſineſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Robert Earle of Leiceſter.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>128</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Earle of Eſſex.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Caeſar Borgia.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>129</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A Court Maxim.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>130</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir Nicholas Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>131</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cornbury Parke.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>131</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Knights.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>French Maſſacre.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>133</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Treaſure.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>134</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Retinue.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry the Fourth.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>135</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Proud Prelate.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>136</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Wentworth.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>137</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Earle of Dorſet.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Philip the ſecond of Spain.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>138</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29474:84"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Collonel Maſſey.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Grand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ignour.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>139</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lady Lambert.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>140</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Olivers Commiſſioners of the Treaſury.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>141</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Harry Martin.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>142</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Bacon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>143</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Monſieur Bellicure.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:84"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Reader is deſired to excuſe the Collector of theſe <hi>Jocoſeria,</hi> iſ in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Names be wanting, for it was neither ſafe, nor ſatisfactory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:85"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Hiſtory of the Commons <hi>War</hi> throughout theſe three Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> The like exact account never before Printed; faithfully Collected by an impartiall Hand: Sold by <hi>Joſhua Coniers</hi> at the black-<hi>Raven</hi> in the long <hi>Walke</hi> neer <hi>Chriſtchurch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:85"/>
            <head>Bookes lately Publiſhed.</head>
            <p>THE Engliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> worth Gold, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with general applauſe, now newly formed into a Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, by the ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of I. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Gent.</p>
            <p>A Compendious Chronicle of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugall,</hi> from <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the firſt King to <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the ſixth, now reigning.</p>
            <p>Thoſe excellent Fancies intituled Don <hi>Juan Lamberto,</hi> or a Comical Hiſtory of our late Times, firſt and ſecond Part, by <hi>Montelion</hi> Knight of the Oracle.</p>
            <p>☞ A new Engliſh Grammer for Forreigners to learn Engliſh, with a Grammer for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> or <hi>Caſtilian</hi> Tongue, with ſpecial Remarkes on the <hi>Portugues</hi> Dialect, for the ſervice of her Majeſty, whom God preſerve.</p>
            <p>The Life and Death of that reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divine and excellent Hiſtorian, Dr. <hi>Thomas Fuller</hi> lately deceaſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:86"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Studii Legalis Ratio,</hi> or Directions for the ſtudy of the Law, under theſe heads, the Qualifications for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Meanes, Method, Time and Place of the Study, by <hi>W. Phillips</hi> of <hi>Grayes</hi> Inn, &amp;c. <hi>price</hi> one ſhilling.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Bookes in the Preſs ready to publiſh this Tearme.</head>
            <p>AN Exact Collection of the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Songs and Poems, from 1639. to 1661. Relating to theſe Times. Written by the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Wits.</p>
            <p>A new Diſcovery of the <hi>French</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe and Running of the Reines, their Cauſes, Signes, with plain and eaſy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of perfect curing the ſame, by <hi>R. Bunworth,</hi> the ſecond Edition cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected with large Additionals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Poor Schollar,</hi> a Comedy.</p>
            <p>All ſold by <hi>H. Marſh</hi> at the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Armes in <hi>Chancery lane</hi> near <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29474:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
